<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Justice upon the armie remonstrance. Or A rebuke of that evill spirit that leads them in their counsels and actions. With a discovery of the contrariety and enmity in their waies, to the good spirit and minde of God. Dedicated to the Generall, and the Councel of War. By William Sedgwick.</title>
            <author>Sedgwick, William, 1609 or 10-1669?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 152 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92861</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2385</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E475_34</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204449</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863939</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863939</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116157</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92861)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116157)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 76:E475[34])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Justice upon the armie remonstrance. Or A rebuke of that evill spirit that leads them in their counsels and actions. With a discovery of the contrariety and enmity in their waies, to the good spirit and minde of God. Dedicated to the Generall, and the Councel of War. By William Sedgwick.</title>
                  <author>Sedgwick, William, 1609 or 10-1669?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Hils, and are to be sold over against S. Thomases Hospitall in Southwark, and for Giles Calvert, at the Black Spread-Eagle at the west end of Pauls, neare Ludgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XLIX. [1649, i.e. 1648]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: England and Wales, Army, Council.  A remonstrance of His Excellency Thomas Lord Fairfax, Lord General of the Parliaments forces. And of the Generall Councell of officers held at St Albans the 16. of November, 1648.</note>
                  <note>Quires A, H and the inner forme of quire G are in the same setting as Wing S2384.</note>
                  <note>Thomason received his copy on December 11, 1648.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Dec: 11."; "1648"; the final X in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army. --  Council. --  Remonstrance of His Excellency Thomas Lord Fairfax, Lord General of the Parliaments forces. And of the generall councell of officers held at St Albans the 16. of November, 1648 --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116157:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Juſtice upon the Armie</hi> REMONSTRANCE. OR A rebuke of that evill ſpirit that leads them in their Counſels and Actions. <hi>With A Diſcovery of the contrariety and enmity in their waies, to the good ſpirit and minde of God.</hi> Dedicated To the Generall, and the Councel of War.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> William Sedgwick.</p>
            <q>
               <p>But they ſhall proceed no further, for their folly ſhall be manifeſt to all men.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2</hi> Tim. <hi>3.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Hils,</hi> and are to be ſold over againſt S. <hi>Thomaſes</hi> Hoſpitall in <hi>Southwark,</hi> and for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the Black <hi>Spread-Eagle</hi> at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> neare <hi>Ludgate</hi> M.DC.XLIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:116157:2"/>
            <head>TO His Excellency <hi>Thomas Lord Fairfax,</hi> GENERALL <hi>Of the Parliaments Forces,</hi> AND To the Generall Councell of Warre.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>o<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> drive furiouſly</hi> over the necks of King and Parliament, Lawes, Covenants, Loyalty, Priviledge, and no humane thing can ſtand before you: You are now fac'd by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and light of God, while you are aſleepe in a darke night of earthly affaires: You have appeald to God in your ſecond Declaration, but did not expect ſo ſuddaine an anſwer: Tis eternall and almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty truth that muſt and will prevaile; if you come into it, 'twill ſave you; if you turne from it, you forſake your <hi>owne mercy;</hi> if you oppoſe it, you daſh your ſelves in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; you cannot goe from it, or beſides it, but into the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of hell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Lord is here <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>braiding your unbeliefe, but mourning over his Jeruſalem<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> with love to your perſons, but with fierce anger againſt your practiſes: I would you had thoſe lively and freſh evidences of your perſonall and everlaſting good in your owne breaſts, as I have; your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſtate is ſure; tis your preſent wandrings that are
<pb facs="tcp:116157:3"/>here condemned; <hi>Blindneſſe hath happened to you in part;</hi> and this is <hi>the time of casting you away;</hi> you will have a time of <hi>being received</hi> againe; you are <hi>now broken off through un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe, you will be graffed in againe:</hi> Tis your <hi>fall</hi> now, you ſhall have a <hi>reſtoring;</hi> you will wonder to behold ſo much <hi>goodneſſe</hi> to your enemies, and ſo much <hi>ſeverity</hi> to you <hi>Oh the depth of the riches both of the wiſedome and knowledge of God! How unſearchable are his judgements, and his wares paſt finding out!</hi> I have <hi>reproved</hi> you <hi>ſharply,</hi> or <hi>cuttingly,</hi> its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for you, <hi>With vengeance to ſave you, and to pull you as fire-brands out of the fire;</hi> your condition requires it; Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is abuſd, mercy deſpiſd, you have a long time tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled upon kindneſſe, and obſtinately refuſed the word of the Lord: You muſt remember my Sermon to you at <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor</hi> upon that Text. Overturne, overturne, overturne; tis Scripture ſtill, and that word lives in and upon you. <hi>Salt-marſh</hi> his meſſage quickly followed it, <hi>Depart from the tents of theſe unrighteous men;</hi> he lives ſtill: And Mr <hi>Pinnels</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition from the Lord following that: Theſe, and other teſtimonies againſt you, have beene ſlighted and diſobey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; your ſinnes grow greater, and the anger of God hotter againſt you; your reprieve is not your ſalvation; you are growne to a height of confidence and preſumption upon your ſucceſſes; <hi>your necks are as iron, and your brows braſſe;</hi> and you walke uncontroulable in your way, triumphing as the onely Princes in the earth, as fit to ſway the Scepter of <hi>England,</hi> and all nations; as the onely righteous, honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble people in the world; the great Lords of the Land<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Therefore it pleaſes me to <hi>powre contempt upon you,</hi> to be ſhod with ſcorne and indignation, and <hi>ſo trample upon Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as morter.</hi> Except I ſhould deale thus with you, you would not be ſenſible of what I ſay, being hardned againſt
<pb facs="tcp:116157:3"/>mercy; and having done all you have done againſt love; <hi>Proſperity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ayes fooles, and therefore the rod is ſit for their backs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know my dealing is juſt and righteous to ſuch as you are, being (as <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l.</hi> 3.18, 19.) <hi>Enemies to the Croſſe of Chriſt;</hi> ſeeming friends to his Goſpell, Miniſtry and Kingdome, but enemies to his <hi>croſſe:</hi> You hate to thinke that thoſe faire <hi>beginnings</hi> of your peace and deliverance, ſhould come to end in ſhame and death; you cannot thinke of leaving your hopes of outward <hi>glory,</hi> and lying down qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly, to let the world trample upon you: This you count folly, <hi>Whoſe end is destruction:</hi> Deſtruction you practiſe, tis your worke, tis your end<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you cant not ſee beyond it, and you are haſtening to it, it is the center to which you tend; and therefore I cannot but ſhew it you, that you may ſtop your courſe before the <hi>pit ſhut her mouth upon you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Whoſe God is their belly;</hi> Your ſaith, underſtanding and God, is ſunke into your bellies, and your rule, your ſtrength, your confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is onely in ſenſuall and brutiſh things; your raiſd ſpirits into the <hi>things of God</hi> are buried in an inferior <hi>region</hi> of groſſe, dull, carnall affaires, and except I ſhould peirce deepe, your <hi>ſlow bellies</hi> would not finde eares: Indeed you are ſo loſt and drownd in ſenſible things of the world, and ſo <hi>eager</hi> in <hi>ſeeking</hi> for thoſe <hi>things</hi> your belly, your carnall affections require of you, that I doubt you will be deafe to what I ſay. <hi>Whoſe glory is in their ſhame;</hi> You are full of <hi>glory</hi> in your <hi>great things</hi> that you have done; <hi>wonderfull things, a mighty preſence of God.</hi> But in ſumme, what is it? You have torne a poore, ſinfull <hi>Kingdome</hi> in pieces; You have executed wrath upon your Brethren, Friends and Country-men; You have laid deſolate your
<pb facs="tcp:116157:4"/>Father the King, the Parliament your Mother, your owne Country; this is your glory to be executioners; <hi>Aſſyria, the rod of my anger:</hi> What a crowne is this? Have you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrored, bleſſed, healed, comforted, ſaved any? No, you have but plunged the Kingdome and your ſelves into a pit of darkneſſe and confuſion: When the things of God are propoſd to you, to ſuffer for others, to love enemies, to doe good to all, to bleſſe all; <hi>you glory in your ſhame,</hi> and ſay, you <hi>ſerve the Lord in this,</hi> and there be <hi>lower</hi> as wel as higher di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſations: You are indeed ſervants of God, ſo was <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar,</hi> ſo is the Devil; and you do the work of <hi>God,</hi> but tis baſe drudgery, tis <hi>his strange worke,</hi> to be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his vengeance; and <hi>tis a lower diſpenſation</hi> indeed, to diſpenſe curſes, not bleſſings, to be <hi>below</hi> in hell, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſd in the wrath of God, not above in heaven in the glory and love of God; and for ſons, heires, ſo you would be thought, to take pleaſure in ſuch mean employment, is vile and unworthy: <hi>Who minde earthly things;</hi> this is another property of yours, your minds are now captiv'd to the earth, deepe in the lower parts of the earth, in the belly and foundations of the earth, pleading the earthly cauſe of earthly people, or digging caves and holes in the earth to ſecure an earthly peace to your ſelves.</p>
            <p>Its high time to withſtand you, and to <hi>rebuke this deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Angel;</hi> for tis not men onely that ſuffer from your vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, but the Lord; your ſword goes ſo deep, <hi>That it peir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thorow his ſoule alſo:</hi> You are gone ſo farre in <hi>diſſolving the foundations of government,</hi> that you are come to him that upholds the <hi>pillars of the earth:</hi> You reach to the <hi>head of principalities and powers,</hi> to the Lord who is the author and upholder of all theſe things; he is in theſe poor, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and deſpiſed Ordinances of his, and ſenſible of every blow that is given to them: <hi>You have digged thorow the wall</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:116157:4"/>of fleſh and men, and broke downe that <hi>partition wall that</hi> divided them from God; and now you are in the bowels of the Lord, theſe miſerable, broken powers are now the Lord: Goe on to teare and rend, you <hi>will at laſt looke upon him whom you have peirced, and mourne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King and Parliament cry unto God in their diſtreſſe, ſaying, <hi>Doubtleſſe thou art our Father, though Abraham be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of us, and Iſrael acknowledge us not, Thou, O Lord art our Father, our Redeemer.</hi> Though you in the greatneſſ of your faith, and confidence in your priviledges, as high as <hi>Abraham and Iſrael</hi> in your literall forme, doe not know them, yet the Lord ownes them, and will heare their cry and deliver them.</p>
            <p>Your proceedings are againſt the Lord; and though you ſay theſe things you do muſt be done till Chriſt come; and when he comes, then tis true, there will need none of theſe things to ſecure your ſelves, but as yet <hi>you must act as men:</hi> In this, you ſay, <hi>your Lord delaies his coming,</hi> and ſo <hi>drunke</hi> with your proſperity and victories, <hi>you beate your fellow ſervants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here you will finde your Lord in an <hi>houre that you were not aware of:</hi> You ſay he will come and deſtroy you and your waies in time, but he is already upon you, and your are not <hi>aware</hi> of it, <hi>and cuts you aſunder;</hi> opens your inward parts, divides the ſecrets of your hearts, and <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points you a portion with hypocrites and unbelievers, where is weeping and gnaſhing of teeth:</hi> You act againſt God, and God againſt you; <hi>Your ſoules loath him, his ſoule loaths you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, Heres nothing written but what is written in your hearts; tis the opening your owne ſoules; tis but what you have feard, and that puniſhment which your owne humiliations and confeſſions have acknowledged juſt and due to you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Nothing but what I have ſuffered for
<pb facs="tcp:116157:5"/>acting in thoſe waies in which you are; <hi>What meaſure hath been meaſured to me by Gad, that doe I meaſure to you:</hi> And as I lay it on you, ſo I ſuffer it with you, and ſhall, be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to ſuffer till you are reſtored from this condition, of ſhame and wrath, to honour and love, and dwell with you in theſe everlaſting burnings, which will purify you from all your filth. Till then, Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am W. Sedgwick.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116157:5"/>
            <head>Juſtice upon the Armie Remonſtrance.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE is, and alwaies hath beene in all things in the world, ſome good, ſome evill, ſome light. ſome darkneſſe: And in this declining ſtate of things, the world growes worſe and worſe, and they that act for it and in it, though under very ſpecious pretences of juſtice, are ſtill more baſe and filthy then thoſe that have, gone before; every generation having a more evill and leſſe good then their predeceſſours. I know there be many good men amongſt you, and that you have ſince the wrack of the Kingdome borne up gallantly, as if you would out-live the ſtorme; That you have worne many favours of God, above, and againſt others; That you have own'd your ſelves to be the people of God, and God by many outward mercies hath own'd you: But in this worke you manifeſtly ſhew, that you <hi>have deeply revolted;</hi> and that <hi>after you had eſcaped the polutions of the world, you are againe entangled therein, and over come; And with the dogge, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to your owne,</hi> and others, <hi>vomit:</hi> to licke up the filth of the world, which others, having drunke the <hi>Wine of the wrath of God,</hi> have ſpued up; <hi>You have beene exalted unto heaven, and are brought down to hell:</hi> You have back-ſlidden from a formall and carnall profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Kingdome of Chriſt living in God, &amp;c. to embrace the taile of <hi>this preſent evill world,</hi> to petty, beggarly, unbelieving, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious projects for ſelfe ſafety. And as you have left God, and waxed wanton, upon his bleſſings, ſo he now hath left you; <hi>hath made your table to become your ſnare;</hi> fatted you up by former mercies, to receive your laſt and greateſt judgements: What you had is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from you, and your wiſedome, majeſty, largeneſſe and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that hath ſometimes appear'd in you in other things, is turn'd now into diſtracted ſtumbers, dark and ſad dreams of ruin, into uncertain, looſe, wandring fancyes of your owne wofull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and abſurd ſhadowes and vaine imaginations of wayes of deliverance: Poore wretches though, angry at you, yet my ſoule
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116157:6"/>pitties you; never were men caught in ſuch a ſnare of the Devill as you are; glorying you are in your owne righteous cauſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident of your innocency and ſucceſſe; And indeed you are ſhut up in a pit of darkneſſe, and already loſt in divine diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p>As there are good men amongſt you, ſo there is, I confeſſe, ſome good lies ſcattered in this Remonſtrance; <hi>The Lord is in it; But as two legges, or a piece of an eare in the mouth of a Lyon.</hi> So torne in pei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and almoſt devoured by that roaring Lyon, that wrathfull, cruell, malicious beaſt, the Devill, that it I ſhould take paines to bring it forth to your view, it would moſt diſpleaſe and offend you; you could not beare the ſight of it, but would your ſelves hate it; therefore I will not looſe my labour in it.</p>
            <p>But the evill part is ſo groſſe and viſible, that I can with moſt eaſe deale with it, and for the preſent with moſt profit to you. And when that heape of dirt and folly is brought forth, and you made ſenſible of it, the good that lyes now buried in it, will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed, and delight to come forth in you. It will be the greateſt mercy to the holy One in you, to give a ſevere ſentence againſt that wicked part that at this time prevailes ſo much in you.</p>
            <p>In dealing with this worke of yours, I ſhall not trouble my ſelf to follow you in all thoſe crooked wayes, confuſed and multiplyed parentheſis, dark and vain tautologies, in which you are loſt and grope: But well knowing your principles upon which you goe, as I finde them expreſſing themſelves, I ſhall ſhew you the evill and folly of them, and that with ſuch plainneſſe, as the wiſer and ſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of you ſhall be convinced and brought forth, the reſt condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in themſelves, and the world may run headlong to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and daſh themſelves in peices againſt that rock of juſtice that fals upon them.</p>
            <p>In the firſt part of your preamble you tell us of your <hi>tender re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the priviledges and freedome of Parliament:</hi> Wherein you deale very deceitfully with the world, and conceale your owne princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; For upon this ground you know you act, that the powers of this world are to be broken into peices; That the Parliament is one of the powers of the world, and that you are called to break them in peices: And therefore it becomes you (you know) to be ſteeld with ſtoutneſſe and reſolution, to trample upon all autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities that ſtand up againſt that juſtice of God that acts you: The priviledge of Parliament is a poore, corrupted thing, to that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary preſence of God that goes with you, and thoſe high
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116157:6"/>undertakings that you have in hand for the publique good, and the eternall ſalvation of the people: You ſhould do as you have done, breake through theſe ſpider-webs of priviledge and freedome of Parliament, and immediatly goe through all to that glorious worke of yours; and not ſuppreſſe your owne principles, to court the world into a deceived opinion of tender regard to them. Indeed the priviledge and freedome of Parliament is gon and loſt long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe, and you doe but fancy one; for a new and true priviledge and freedome doth not yet appeare to you, neither can you owne them.</p>
            <p>In the next part of your preamble you tell us the reaſons of your preſent declaring your ſelves, becauſe things are <hi>[brought to the utmoſt criſis of danger]</hi> Tis true this, but you make a very ill uſe of it: There is two in the Kingdome, the holy one our life, peace, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, agreement, &amp;c. whom you have not ſeene yet: and a wicked one, which is wrath, malice, death, revenge, &amp;c. Theſe two are now conflicting together: The holy one would eſtabliſh love, bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one with another, forgiving one another, ſelfe-deniall, &amp;c. The deſtroyer would continue miſcheifs, warres, accuſations, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties, &amp;c. The contention growes ſharpe, and the evill one ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his utmoſt and laſt reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>Now we that ſee the power of truth and love, are at reſt, being aſſured, that the righteous Lord is above all.</p>
            <p>But here you come with your wofull feares, and ſay <hi>[which cals upon every man to contribute what helpe be can:]</hi> Doe not you know yet, <hi>that vaine is the helpe of man:</hi> You and all men come to offer helpe, but it is to a wicked world, to bring fuell to the fire of wrath; for feare, miſery and deſtruction ſhould ceaſe raging; <hi>Ceaſe from man whoſe breath is in his noſtrils:</hi> A proud and empty thing: and ceaſe you fooliſh men from blowing the coales of diviſion amongſt us: <hi>(And ſeeing, no effectuall helpe from elſe where appeare)</hi> your curſe is not to <hi>ſee when good comes: Wee ſee ſalvation is nigh them that fear him, that glory may dwell in cur land; God a preſent helpe in the time of trouble:</hi> You are blinde, and cannot ſee the Lord our effectuall Saviour An enemy would make this ſenſe of your words: Warre is your life, and ſeeing peace ready to come, and no effectuall helpe appeares to lengthen out miſery, and deſtroy the Treaty, you will doe it.</p>
            <p>And now you give us the ground of your undertaking th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s worke, <hi>(Conſcience, and duty to God and men obliges)</hi> you ſleighty paſſe over this which ſhould be fully cleared; and the reaſon is, you
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116157:7"/>are not upon a ſound foundation; nor dare you come to a ſtrict examination of your owne ground, but are hurried on blindly, upon weake paſſions of feare, jealouſy, neceſſity, &amp;c. without any ſound bottome. This likewiſe I obſerve from your words here, and from ſome conference with ſome of you, that you know not which of theſe two to take for your principle, God or man; but are in a luke-warme condition, neither hot nor cold; neither hot enough in the ſpirit of God, to doe all things in a divine way: nor ſo cold, as to ſubmit to the lawes of men. In diſcourſe with ſome of you againſt your proceedings, that they were contrary to the royall law, the Will and Way of our Father; Which is, <hi>To doe good to them that hate us, and perſecute us; to forgive our enemies; to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come evill with good; to conquer by eſuffering and love:</hi> They have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, that in theſe things they act as men, in a civill reſpect; which in you that own your ſelves to be godly, ſpiritual men, and to have the power of godlineſſe, is great impiety: For you in your affaires openly and profeſſedly to decline the perfect way of Chriſt, and goe to the wayes of the Heathen; to lay aſide, exclude and thruſt out the heavenly man and his light, that you may pleaſe your ſelves in the darkneſſe of men. You do fully manifeſt not being Chriſtian, divine, holy in all things, that truly you are ſo in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and ſo your religion is vaine: Or that you are fallen from God to man; <hi>You begun in the ſpirit, and end in the fleſh, and ſo Chriſt is of none effect at all;</hi> for he that doth not doe all things in the power of God, he doth nothing in it: You forget that ſpeech of Saint <hi>Paul, You walke as men, are you not carnall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When we ſay, if you will walke as men, you muſt ſubmit to your Governours, live under humane Laws, and be ſubject to them: then you fly from ſuch ordinary things to an extraordinary call, as <hi>Phineas;</hi> to be carried by the mighty power and preſence of God: that you in all things are as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the wilderneſs; to have a <hi>Pillar</hi> of <hi>Cloud</hi> by day, and <hi>Fire</hi> by night to goe before you: Thus you <hi>halt between two opinions,</hi> and <hi>gad about to change your way;</hi> and are true to nothing, neither God nor man; but become as thoſe Beaſts in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> that have many heads and <hi>crowns</hi> upon them: your waies are beaſtly, cruel, abſurd, monſtrous with many heads; yet you'l be crown'd with the moſt glorious titles of the preſence of God, the people of God, the cauſe of God: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore know this, though you would ſhuffle up your ground work, <hi>Conſcience and duty to God and men,</hi> you ſhall not: For a conſcience
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116157:7"/>guided by the wiſdom &amp; power of God ſcornes ſuch baſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy waies as you walk in: &amp; thoſe men that you think are far below you ſcorn to lift up themſelves above theit ſuperiours, and to Lord it over King and Parliament as you doe; nor dare conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s againſt command of God and men, and uphold a company of vile and wicked wrecches (only for their own ſafety) to the waſting and deſtroying of their Country.</p>
            <p>Now you begin another part of your preamble, wherein you ſay that that rule of <hi>Salus populi, ſuprema lex, is of all others moſt apt to be abuſed:</hi> You have all pretended to this maxim, but have miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly abuſed it, and the people too: a company of deceivers and mountebanks that talk of curing, ſaving, delivering, but all waſt, ſpoyle and deſtroy the people.</p>
            <p>We ſhall ere long ſee, that <hi>Suprema lex,</hi> that law of love, the mercy and goodneſſe of the moſt high God, is onely <hi>Salus populi,</hi> the ſalvation of the People of <hi>England;</hi> its miſſe-applyed ſo long as any man aſſumes it to himſelfe.</p>
            <p>And here for two or three pages you are <hi>trimming your way to ſeek love</hi> as the Prophet ſaith; you put an excellent dreſſe upon your work, and daub over a <hi>rotten ſepulchre,</hi> wherein there is nothing but <hi>dead mens bones;</hi> with a ſhew of wiſdome, as if you would out the haire of juſtice, and goe away more exact then all that have gone before you; a pure medium 'tween all excreams; avoiding all the rocks of <hi>Levellers</hi> and <hi>Cavaliers;</hi> of all raſhnes and evil intentions, in which work you wrap up your ſelves in ſuch a mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of circum-locutions, and are in ſuch a wood of long and tedious expreſſions that as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaies, <hi>Are too wonderfull for me!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You are in this diſcourſe, <hi>An Eagle in the aire;</hi> carried a loft by the prince of the ayre in your owne fancyes: <hi>A ſerpent on a rocke, a crooked ſerpent,</hi> winding and turning this way and that way upon a rocke of confidence of God and your owne wiſedome. <hi>A ſhip in the midſt of the ſea:</hi> You are gone from all firme land, from all ſolid principles of goodneſſe, and are toſſed about in a ſea of weakneſſe and confuſion. <hi>And the way of a man with a maid:</hi> You are luſting af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter your Miſtris, honour; and to enjoy her, nimbly fly from one ſecret place to another to hide your ſelves from ſhame: ſuch is the way of your adulterous ſpirits; being gone from your husband, the Lord, to the world: <hi>You eate up</hi> King, Parliament and People, to ſatisfie your carnall love of ſafety and an outward Kingdome, and <hi>wipe your mouths</hi> with ſome fine language, and <hi>ſay you have done no
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116157:8"/>wickedneſſe:</hi> you may deceive your ſelves, but can't deceive either God or man: 'tis very plain, that when you have multiplied your vain words, your <hi>ſwelling words</hi> to juſtify your ſelves, it is but the <hi>atire of a harlot;</hi> and every one wil ſee that you doe <hi>but darken coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel by words without knowledge;</hi> and while you think to make your ſelves more vendible, you make your ſelves more abominable.</p>
            <p>There be many particulars in this part worth anſwering; but thoſe things wherein any ſhew of ſtrength lies, you make often uſe of them, and wee ſhal meet with them againe he reafter, and therefore for preſent ſhal paſſe them over.</p>
            <p>From the ſeventh to the twelfth page, you are relating how the Parliament <hi>Voted no more addreſſes,</hi> and <hi>how they were turned into this courſe of the Treaty.</hi> It were exceeding eaſy to ſhew in ſeveral parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, of your diſcourſe, that you doe, in favour to your ſelves, abuſe the Parliament and others; and in moſt things accuſe others of thoſe things that you your ſelves are guilty of: but I ſhal leave that to ſome other Pen that loves to deale in ſuch things: I would in al things diſcover to you how unchriſtian your charges are; In ſumme, you here lay open the inſtability of the Parliament, and by what means they were toſſed from one thing to another, and ſo declare the evil practiſes of the Kings party; in both you are very large, and very harſh to both; without any <hi>molifying oyle,</hi> or mirigating mercy; having nothing elſe in your eye but to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver your own ſhame, and as fully as you can, diſcover others, to eaſe your ſelves and load others: Tis Chriſts worke to excuſe others, and pity them, <hi>Father forgive them they know not what they doe;</hi> and to take the burthen and guilt upon himſelfe, to <hi>bear our ſinnes; he is made ſinne for us:</hi> but 'tis your work to condemn others, and juſtify your ſelves Chriſt pities others when he ſuffers by their hands: you are cruel and mercileſſe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers when they ſuffer under your hands: ſuch infinite diſtance is there between your ſpirits, and the Spirit of the Lord.</p>
            <p>The poor Parliament, for their ſinnes, are ſhattered and broken, ful of perplexity; the whole Kingdome ful of diſcontent againſt them; and they reeling this way and that way to ſave themſelves and the Kingdome, and know not how to doe it.</p>
            <p>The Kings party for their ſinnes, likewiſe lying under ſore bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, heavy preſſures, and ſtrugling to get from under their into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable afflictions, but can't. And in al theſe afflictions, our Lord
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116157:8"/>is afflicted, and bears al our infirmities, they lie upon Chriſts ſhoulders; and you ſeeing the Kingdome, and the Lord of the Kingdome) lying like the poor man, traveling from <hi>Jeruſalem to Jericho,</hi> wounded and halfe dead; not onely paſſe by, as the <hi>Prieſt</hi> and the <hi>Levite,</hi> and leave it to ſinke under its miſery; but delight to tear and rend its wounds, to keep them open that they may bleed continually: In al not a Word of peace or pity to any; as dry and hard as the rock: you have no balm at al for our wounds, nothing of the good <hi>Samaritan:</hi> but <hi>vineger,</hi> piercing, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing, condemning ſpeeches; as <hi>Fleſh-flies,</hi> living upon the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trified ſores, ſo doe you finde eaſe, pleaſure, and life to your cauſe upon the filth and ruine of the Nation: In this you are as the man poſſeſſed with the Devil, you are led by a dark, foul ſpirit, to walke and live amongſt the graves, converſing with the dead car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſſe of the Kingdome; <hi>you ſtretch out the line of confuſion</hi> upon the Kingdome, and gather together <hi>the ſtones of emptineſſe:</hi> you <hi>make long furrowes upon the backs of the people,</hi> intend our ruine to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt; and bring in to our deſolate Nation, <hi>the wild beaſt of the deſert to meet with wild beaſts of the Iſlands; the Satyre to cry to his fellow, the Screech-Owle, and the great Owle to lay and hatch; and the Vultures with their mates: all theſe dance together</hi> in your diſcourſe, which is black as pitch, dark and uncomfortable as the night, and threatning to add miſery upon miſery upon us, and not a ſillable of healing mercy in any: ſure your nature is to take pleaſure, to wallow and tumble in our Nations woes. Give me leave to tel the ſtoryaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you, and to relate the buſineſſe thus.</p>
            <p>Once our King and Parliament, or People, lived quietly and lovingly together, imbraced in the armes of divine goodnes, proſpered together as Husband and Wife, till their iniquities on both ſides broke this union: and being parted by their jealouſies and luſts, after many unkinde blowes betwixt them; The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Wife, in a high rage, at the remembrance of al her Lords unkindneſſe, and giving too much eare to her own paſſion, and the accuſations of adultery, and provoaked by a multitude of perplexities, Voted no move Addreſſes: Shee would have nothing to doe with her Husband, but would forſake him for ever and be divorced from him; and then you who alwaies have luſted after the Royal Bed, encourage her with thanks, and court her for your ſelves.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:116157:9"/>
            <p>But ere long the natural1 affections of theſe two divided friends, though much clogd with jealouſies and diſcontents, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to work towards each other, which may be interrupted for a ſeaſon, but cannot be totally extinguiſht: The Parliament find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing but diſtraction, diſhonour, with ſcorn and miſery in a ſolitary ſtate, and finding her ſelfe unable to ſatisfie her unquiet children without their Father, begins to thinke how ſhee may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain recover her own head and husband, and to this purpoſe Voted a perſonal Treaty with the King.</p>
            <p>And now we are fallen upon the principal and main ſubject of your Remonſtrance, to ſhew the evil and danger of this Perſonal Treaty, in <hi>page</hi> 12. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> you fall directly upon <hi>(this miſerable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience of a Perſonall Treaty)</hi> and elſewhere <hi>(miſerable inſnaring Treaty)</hi> It ſeems this Treaty doth very much offend, you declare ſo bitterly againſt it: Tis true, while things are at this imperfect ſtate, it is a very eaſy matter to accuſe or condemne any perſon or thing, but a hard matter to juſtifie or ſave any thing; that's the worke of the devil, this is the work of God. I confeſſe this Treaty is a poor, low, dark thing, neither party managing of it with that clearnes &amp; brightnes of love and goodneſſe that I could wiſh: that it doth not for the preſent give <hi>ſatisfaction to any ſide: &amp; being infirm</hi> you have great advantage in appearing againſt it, and ſome ſhew of reaſon for it; and therefore your acting againſt it may doe ſome good to cleare it from ſome evill that adheres to it: for this is my minde, you nor none elſe can doe any hurt to him, or them, that are truly good: but all things, be they never ſo evill in themſelves, worke together unanimouſly and conſtantly for their good: For this Treaty, <hi>there is a bleſſing, deſtroy it not;</hi> the ſeed of peace is in it, and it wil thrive and flouriſh; act what you can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, you cannot deſtroy peace or union, thats the Lords.</p>
            <p>In this darke buſineſſe where the King and Parliament are gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping together to finde a little eaſe and reſt for themſelves, being wearied with the miſeries of war, doth the Lord come as a theefe in the night; ſo that if both parties ſhould deſigne by it to coſen the world, and one another, the thieſe would cozen them both: I meane, ſteale away their evill luſts and ſinnes, and bring good out of it againſt the deſignes of men; and if you would trample upon it, becauſe its low and poor; and be jealous of it as dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and inſnaring; he will deceive you too, and make it for your good and peace as wel as others, and againſt your preſent thoughts
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116157:9"/>of ſtrife, ſteale into your breaſts, and beget love and peace there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. This is the robbery of this thiefe in the night, to ſteale away evill from us, and ſurprize us with good.</p>
            <p>Your fiery contention therefore againſt it will be very uſefull; twill burne up thoſe doubts and feares that are on either ſide; melt each other into a cloſer union: The root of it being the divine love; all you doe againſt it will but quicken that principle, and ſpur them on to a more hearty and earneſt cloſing: and while you endeavour to rende them from each other, they will clapſe the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter about each other, and turne all their contention againſt you, who from your preſent promoting of differences, will be ſuſpected to be the authors of all their ſtrife.</p>
            <p>Let us now examine the reaſons you give againſt a Treaty, pag. 14, &amp;c. You firſt quere, and then declare, that it is not <hi>juſt and good, nor ſafe;</hi> and ſo all along you inſiſt upon theſe two things, <hi>ſatis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and ſecurity;</hi> To prove the juſtice of it, you ſtate the intereſts of the Kingdome and Parliament, as they have beene the matter of our quarrel: In which we finde theſe faults.</p>
            <p>Firſt, You would make your owne and the publique intereſt to be one; they are ſo much different, that you are faine to patch them up together often, and bring in yours in a parentheſis; as here, pag. 14. <hi>(though even the particular ſafety of ſuch as have engaged for the publique is not to be neglected)</hi> In this and in the reſt of your diſcourſe, it appeares, you conceive your ſelves neglected and left out in the Treaty; and you do by this require your own inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to be conſidered; and that's very obſtructive to peace, for men in a diſtracted Kingdom to uphold a particular intereſt, thwarting the generall, peace and union, the common intereſt of all States, and with violence to enforce it to the ruine of the whole.</p>
            <p>That which you offer to us is not the publique, but your parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular intereſt; which indeed is not your intereſt neither, but a rent and diviſion an erroneous opinion. For that there be <hi>a common and ſupreame councell, that the power of making lawes, chuſing officers, puniſhing offendors, be in them, &amp;c.</hi> Its very apparent that this is not halfe the intereſt of the Kingdome, tis much too narrow for a rich, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable nation: Generally you know the people of <hi>England</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire peace, ſetled religion, eſtabliſht truth, freedome of trade, and this with His Majeſty, under their King, that he may govern them according to their honeſt and knowne lawes, that they may live in proſperity and honour: For theſe deviſed things, you propoſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116157:10"/>the people know them not, affect them leſſe then know them; they are invented onely to pleaſe and ſecure your ſelves, and to pul downe Monarchy, againſt which you would make your ſelves irreconcileable: Theſe principles are but the ax or knife, to prune and cut the extravagancies of Monarchy or tyranny; and if al the Kingdome were an ax or knife, we were in an ill caſe: You are but a part, and alas, an inconſiderable part; not one of an hundred will owne what you ſet downe as the publique intereſt; and a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſed part; a bone ſtarted out of his place; a piece of timber, that is gone from the whole frame of the Kingdome, which is large, and conſiſts of King, Lords, Commons, with innumerable, excellent branches growing out of theſe.</p>
            <p>Now this were a ſtrange cure, to breake off the bones in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, to bring the whole to one diſ-jointed part, or to force the whole houſe to come after one piece that is ſtarted out, is il work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip. Tis a ſtrange thing that men ſhould place the welfare of the Kingdome in ſuch inconſiderable things: Methinks tis a wonder, that men ſhould bring forth ſome pedantick conceits, and then magnifie them ſo farre, as entitle them to the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Thus will meane and narrow ſpirits doe, when they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude themſelves into publique affaires: When ſouldiers, men of private ſpirits, confident of their ability and judgement in greateſt matters, ſhall produce brats of their owne braine, and impoſe them upon the nation, we ſhall be ſlaves indeed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That you that are Chriſtians, that talke of the reign of Chriſt and of the Saints, ſhould now engage your ſelves to ſo baſe an intereſt as this is; that you will eſpouſe ſo poore a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, which, in ſumme; is to throw downe a King and Lords, and ſet up the people: <hi>That all power ſhould be in the hands of the Parliament, and that to be certaine, and in the hands of a ſubordinate officer to call, &amp;c.</hi> Will the eſtabliſhing of this ſatisfie you for all the bloudſhed, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates ruin'd, &amp;c? is this your ſatisfaction? ſhould you not rather propoſe, that all power, and dominion, and reigne ſhould be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Lord, that King, and Parliament, and People, and all ſhould be filled with the righteouſneſſe and goodneſſe of God? But theſe things are too good to be ſpoken of, beyond your faith ever to ſee it: But I'le tell you, if this be not your intereſt to have God all in all, to fill every thing, and to have all things offered up to him in truth and righteouſneſſe: your intereſt and Gods are more divided then yours and the Kings; and if you adhere to that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116157:10"/>you have propoſd, you forſake your owne intereſt, and eſpouſe the Devils, the God of this world, the Deſtroyer, and will periſh with him.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, This is a fault that you all along carry the intereſt of the publique in opposition to the Kings; which is a wicked thing to divide them that God hath joined: wherein you doe, as ſword; men, cut in pieces, and indeed deſtroy and mangle, not onely the Kingdome, but the word, Intereſt, which is of a uniting ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>inter eſſe</hi> is to be in or amongſt each other: The publique hath its intereſt in the King, and the King his intereſt in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique; or they have the ſame <hi>eſſe,</hi> or intereſt, which is to be toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in each other; the King is in the people, and the people in the King; the Kings being is not abſolute, or alone, but an inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, as he is in union with, and relation to his people, which are his ſtrength and life; and the peoples being is not naked or ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, but an intereſt in the greatneſſe and wiſedome of their King, who is their life and honour: And though you will diſ-join your ſelves from Kings, God will not, neither will I; God is King of Kings; Kings and Princes God, as well as peoples; their, God as well as ours, and theirs eminently, as that ſpaech enforces God of <hi>Iſrael, Iſrael,</hi> God above all the nations; ſo King of Kings, Kings God more then of common men; and by neare and eſpeciall kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and communion; aſſuming their titles and honour, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them his majeſty and dominion; Kinglineſſe agrees with all Chriſtians who are of a royall nature, made Kings with Chriſt, and cannot but be friends to it, being of kin to it; the children of God, borne of the King of heaven, are men of honour (not in a baſe, vaine way, but in a true, juſt way) and if there be not Kings to honor, they would want, objects to beſtow that fulnes of honon that is in their breaſts; would loſe the greateſt part of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, which is majeſty and glory, would want occaſion of expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their high and noble ſpirits: It's a baſtard religion that is incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the majeſty and greatneſſe of the moſt abſolute Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch; and ſuch ſpirits are ſtrangers from the Kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and know not the glory in which God lives, and are of nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and evill mindes that are corrupt themſelves, and not able to beare greatneſſe, and ſo thinke God will not, or cannot qualifie men for ſuch high places, with anſwerable and proportionable power and, goodneſſe: You are indeed much in the fleſh, in a form of religion which is weake and of a parting nature, cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116157:11"/>nor comprehend things in union; you are dividing ſtill tweene heaven and earth, 'tweene God and King; you can't own them in union, and so divide King and people: but the ſpirit of God is large, and reconciles, compoſes, gathers all into one, into Chriſt; God and man into one perſon; head and members into one body. This love you know not, that embraces God and the King in one perſon, and King and people in one body.</p>
            <p>A fourth fault is, in your further ſtating of the controverſy 'tweene King and Parliament, you bring in, in the ſecond place, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; the order ſhewes the preſent frame of your ſpirits, firſt the world, and then godlineſſe: But in this you erre exceedingly, in putting all the enmity againſt godlineſſe and the power of it, on the Kings part, and charging it upon him as his intereſt, and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming all religion and godlineſſe to your ſelves.</p>
            <p>Upon this ground ſtands much of the controverſy betweene the Cavaliers and you; that they are wicked, you godly; they ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to God, you Saints; they darkneſſe, you light, and therfore as you ſay afterward, <hi>What fellowſhip hath light with darkneſſe?</hi> This is a ground (if it ſtand good) of an everlaſting quarrell; and if it fals, I hope ſome of the edge of your contention may be taken off.</p>
            <p>The anſwer of this is as proper for me as any; who, you know, doe well underſtand the utmoſt of the religion you walke in, and have beene exerciſd in it with as much exactneſſe, faithfulneſſe, power and comfort as any of you: Your consciences, many of you, can beare witneſſe of the uprightneſſe and efficacy of my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation amongſt you; and that I was, when I was with you, not onely a companion, but a leader to you in the beſt things: and ſince have beene tryed by very great ſufferings, and made a ſpectacle to God and men, and beene publiquely ſet up as a marke, for all men to ſhoot their opinions and judgements at, and dare challenge the whole earth, the Lord being my Righteouſneſſe to accuſe me of any injuſtice to God or man: and now muſt teſtifie concerning you and my ſelf with you, that that way wherein you walke is not the <hi>power of godlineſſe,</hi> but a poore, weake, fleſhly form.</p>
            <p>You are indeed Saints by intention, counſell, hope; you aime at it, looke for it: but in your preſent ſtate you are carnall, and walke in the fleſh in great infirmity: that your ſtate at beſt was but to be as the Jewes, having a forme of knowledge according to the letter of the law: which forme is now corrupted, left and forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of God, and you are become, through blindneſſe &amp; ignorance,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116157:11"/>enemies to the ſpirit, and to the Croſſe of Chriſt: You live not the life of Chriſt; you are not dead to the world, nay, you op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that death; you will not ſuffer with Chriſt; you have not the ſpirit of God; walke not in your affaires in the wiſedom and ſtrength of God, nor in the love of God; you know not the minde of God, have not communion with God; what ever you doe, or have done, you doe it by the ſtrength of man, and not by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God; and now leſt to a poore, blinde, unſtable way, not knowing whether you goe, <hi>your waies being darke and ſlippery,</hi> and yet glorying in fleſhly and outward things; miſtaking earthy and common bleſſings for heavenly and inward; crying up the <hi>Lord, the Lord,</hi> when you doe the workes of the Devill: The Holy God will no longer ſuffer you to wear thoſe names of Saints and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but <hi>will caſt dung upon your ſolemne feaſts, and curſe your bleſſings,</hi> and diſcover you to be but <hi>whited ſepulchres,</hi> and cauſe your rottenneſſe to come forth, <hi>uncover your nakedneſſe</hi> before the nation, that al may abhorre and loath that outward, formall religion which you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe; it doth and will more ſtinke in the noſtrils of thoſe people that have no knowledge of God, to ſee pride, ſelf-love, contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the world, rebellion, falſhood, folly and hatred of God, to be in ſuch zealous pretenders to the ſpirit of God.</p>
            <p>As you have not the power of godlineſſe, ſo you have many vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, groſſe luſts and evill principles which morall men doe op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in you; you are not pure, nor is it onely for your purity (as you ſuppoſe) that the Kings party oppoſe you, but for your with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſome things that are good in them, and ſuch as their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences are bound by God to proſecute; though there be that wickedneſſe in many of them too, to hate that of God that hath appeared in you, becauſe different from theirs: but their oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not directly againſt the face of God, for that never ſhin'd forth clearly in us, but againſt that particular form, as deſtructive to theirs, and our carnall principles which were contrary to theirs, and thoſe obſcured with many infirmities too: ſo that tis high pride for us to thinke that we are all Saints, godly, &amp;c. and they enemies to God, becauſe to us.</p>
            <p>And 2. It is as much uncharitableneſſe to judge them, as altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the darke; for though they are indeed viſibly in greater looſeneſſe many of them, and more in the condition of the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, living more manifeſtly according to the courſe of the world, &amp;c. yet in many things you have juſtified their principles as more righteous then yours; and many of their perſons
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116157:12"/>more ſober, patient, loving, gentle, yea more knowing and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning in the things of God then you: And though there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt that party the greateſt, viſible and morall wickedneſſe, yet there is among you the greateſt enmity and malignancy to the ſpirit of God; the greateſt pride, hypocriſy, ſelfe confidence, and ſpirituall wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>And this you will know that thus judge after the fleſh, that thoſe <hi>Publicans and Harlots ſhall enter into the Kingdome of God before you:</hi> Many of them <hi>ſhall come from the Eaſt and from the Weſt,</hi> and from the remoteſt parts of the earth, and greateſt diſtance from God, <hi>and ſit downe with Abraham, Iſaac and Jacob in the Kingdome of God, and you ſhall be thruſt out:</hi> Therefore this manner of judging of yours, of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting them evill, and your ſelves good, is one of <hi>thoſe ſtrong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions</hi> ſpoken of; whereby you are,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Led to the deſtroying of others as righteous as your ſelves.</p>
            <p>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>condly, Kept off from the ſight of your owne iniquities, and and making warre with them: for indeed theſe two parties are within you; and if you were not kept by this formally, fleſhly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of ſinne in others, you would have no other contention but with ſinne in your owne breaſts, to deſtroy thoſe workes of the Devill in which you are bound.</p>
            <p>Till you lay downe this fleſhly warre with others, and begin that ſpirituall warre with Antichriſt, Malignants, &amp;c. in your owne hearts you will never have peace: And to ſatisfie you and all parts in the Kingdome concerning theſe oppoſitions and conteſts in religious matters, tis thus.</p>
            <p>All men are in the darke, and know not the whole body of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine truth, onely lay hold each of ſome part of it; So that <hi>truth,</hi> which is one in it ſelfe in, and amongſt the darkneſſe of men is divided, cut in pieces, and lies ſcattered about here and there; and every one holds what ha holds in enmity and contrariety to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and through pride and malice with that good that is in him, oppoſes God and goodneſſe in others; that by this all may be aſhamed and broken in pieces, and become guilty before God, and made at laſt to come downe from their proud conceits, and ſee they are fooles, <hi>and know nothing as they ought to know,</hi> and to be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to learne of others.</p>
            <p>After you have ſtated the controverſy to prove the injuſtice of an accommodation, you fall upon the King, judging him in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116157:12"/>higheſt manner, as guilty of the fouleſt treaſon, murder, &amp;c. and that too in a moſt unpardonable and irreconcilable way, as inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of mercy, and beyond all peace and accommodation: There is nothing wherein the Devill is more exerciſd, then in accuſing; from which he hath his name: and there is nothing wherein he hath more corrupted the nature of man in theſe laſt daies, then this; it being that generall forme into which he hath caſt the ſpirits of men, whence they are called, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.3. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Accuſers, or in plaine Engliſh, Devils: Men are now very ordinarily, and with a ſhew of juſtice, Devils one to another.</p>
            <p>This is common amongſt men, eſpecially amongſt religious and profeſſing men; The Scribes and Phariſees, men in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt forme of religion, are the moſt guilty of it, thinking ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily that they have right to judge; and this is notoriouſly your ſinne in this worke. To deſtroy it in you and others, we ſhall ſet ſet out the evill of it, as it hath beene expreſſed in ſome Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Thou art unexcuſable, Oh man, whoſoever thou art, that judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt;</hi> God hath reſerved the authority of judgement to himſelfe, who is and will be <hi>Judge of all;</hi> its proper for God onely, who knowes hearts; who onely knowes good and evill; who can ſave as well as deſtroy; and therefore not fit for man, who can do nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good nor evill; at beſt he cannot ſave, and therefore moſt unfit to be a judge: Therefore you, whoſoever you are, be you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo good men, religious men, bleſt with never ſo great favours, you have nothing to doe to judge while you are men.</p>
            <p>If it be objected, then there ſhould be no Judges amongſt men. I anſwer, Judges are Gods; <hi>I have ſaid ye are Gods:</hi> and if they have not the power and goodnes of God, as wel as the place and title, they are Idols, Heathen Gods; and when we ſay, <hi>God is Judge alone,</hi> we meane not God out of, but in man; or man taken up into the Righteouſneſſe and Authority of God, man ſanctified by God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Man, a judge, is inexcuſable; he that will be a judge, is ſuppoſed to be ſo high in holineſſe, ſo innocent as needs no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe; he that is in the nature of God, tis a ſhame for him to think of an excuſe, Tis my infirmity, I am a ſinner; but I have a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour: Tis a dangerous thing therefore, being men, and needing excuſe for your weakneſſe, that you preſume to be judges, and put
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116157:13"/>your ſelves out of excuſe; you cannot ſay you are ignorant, no, you are wiſe judges; you cannot ſay you are weake, no, you are ſtrong to ſentence others; you cannot ſay you are ſinners, being judges of the law you may not be thought breakers.</p>
            <p>Or for a vile man to lift up himſelfe in the place of God, to be ſo ſottiſhly blinde in himſelfe, as not to ſee his owne filthineſſe, and conceive himſelf a God, it's a preſumption that admits of no excuſe tis ſo groſs: or for a man to be ſo cruel to his brother as to judge him and thruſt him out of the grace of God, is ſo Diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical, as there's no excuſe for it; by doing this men ſhew them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſelves Devils, for whom there's no mercy, no favour.</p>
            <p>It follows, <hi>For wherein thou judgeſt another, thou condemneſt thy ſelfe; for thou that judgeſt doſt the ſame things.</hi> There is a fellowſhip in evill as in good: every man while he is a ſinner hath in him whatever a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſinner hath; as every righteous man hath what ever another righteous man hath: If you judge any part of your nature, you judge the whole: If a man that lives in the world, then your ſelves, your ſpirits, principles, actions, which are all worldly and ſinfull: Eſpecially and particularly, what ever any party accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes another of concerning theſe warres, they themſelves doe the ſame things: To inſtance in the preſent caſe.</p>
            <p>You judge the King guilty of breaking Covenant, of betraying truſt, have we not broke our oath of Allegiance to him, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed the truſt he put in his people? and have not we likewiſe betrayed that truſt the Parliament put in us, when after promiſes of ſubjection to them, the Army refuſed, and made warre with them?</p>
            <p>You judge him guilty of all the bloud, rapine, ſpoile: Dare any man ſay he is not guilty of it? Were we abſolute in taking up armes, in proſecuting the warre, in continuing in armes? Is there not in all, ſelf-love, malice, revenge, envy, diſtruſt of God? Had we beene rightly carried in freeing <hi>England</hi> from oppreſſion, we had freely laid downe our lives in a voluntary ſuffering, and that would have ſaved the Kingdome; whereas by our raſh running to force, we are guilty of the miſeries of warre as well as the King: But in continuing the Army after your enemies ſubdued, you are manifeſtly guilty of the preſent oppreſſion upon the poore people; of the intolerable burden of free-quarter, and unreaſonable taxes.</p>
            <p>You charge him for ſeeking to ſet up his owne intereſt of will
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:116157:13"/>and power. Doe you not doe the ſame thing? What doe you now but ſet up will and power? Going beſide all Law and right, to ſet up the worſt will and power, the will and power of People, of the ſword: Therefore let me expoſtulate with you, as that Apoſtle, <hi>Thou that ſaieſt a man ſhould not ſteal, doeſt thou ſteal? &amp;c.</hi> Thou that haſt ſo much light as to oppoſe tyranny, art thou the verieſt tyrant? Thou that plead'ft for Laws, art thou greateſt violater of Laws? We will goe further with the Apoſtle; <hi>Thou that abhorreſt Idols, doeſt thou commit ſacriledge?</hi> You abhorre his waies as groſſe; but you have more ſecret and cloſe iniquities; you rob God even of his Throne, ſetting up your formal religion in the place of God: you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of ſhedding innocent blood, and you ſhed the truly innocent blood of Chriſt: Of Rapine and ſpoyle, and you daily ſpoyle the Temple of God, your own bodies and ſoules with your noyſome luſts. Afterwards <hi>verſe</hi> 3. <hi>Thinkeſt thou this, O man, that judgeſt them that doe ſuch things, and doeſt the ſame, that thou ſhalt eſcape the judgement of God?</hi> He that judgeth is guilty, and his guilt begins to ſtir in him: God begins to write bitternes in the conſcience, and then to ſave himſelfe, he begins to judge others; judgement of men is the conſtant effect of troubled ſpirits; and this is your condition, you are reſtleſſe in your ſelves, you finde God frowning upon you for your ſinnes, that makes you ſeeke for <hi>fatis faction for blood, that it may be expiated, and the wrath of God appeaſed:</hi> The fire is kindled in your owne hearts, <hi>your tongues are ſet on fire of hell.</hi> If you had the peace of God upon true grounds you would be ſtill; or if your conſciences were beſprinckled with the blood of Chriſt, you would not ſeek for expiation: But there is the voice of <hi>thy brothers blood, the blood of: Abel cries, not the blood</hi> of Chriſt. The blood of Chriſt, if you knew it, cries peace, reconciliation, union, favour, love, taking away enmity. The bloud of <hi>Abel</hi> for revenge, for juſtice: this is your voice, which ſhews, a <hi>Cains</hi> ſpirit; you are troubled for your ſinnes; <hi>Thinkeſt thou to eſcape the righteous judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God,</hi> no, thou art running farther into it; you are not quitting your ſelves, but increaſing your evils: <hi>Or deſpiſeſt thou the riches of his goodneſſe:</hi> God hath been gracious unto you, and re priev'd you for a while from deſtruction; doe you thus abuſe it to harden your hearts to pride, malice and wicked inſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting over your brethrent is this the uſe of your Victories, to have oportunities to doe more miſchiefe? <hi>And ſo trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure up wrath for your ſelves:</hi> For all that you lay upon
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116157:14"/>others, you, provide it and ſtore it up for your ſelves. God hath declar'd, you know, rich mercie to the King and his party, in my Booke called, <hi>The Leaves of the Tree of Life:</hi> You deſpiſe this rich mercy, ſcorne it, and ſet up your mercyleſſe juſtice againſt it; <hi>Not knowing that the goodneſſe of God leades to repentance:</hi> you require re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance before mercy: Gods goodneſſe goes before, and leads to repentance; and that goodneſſe that hath beene manifeſt, though you ignorantly deſpiſe it, counting it folly and madneſſe, upon no other ground but becauſe tis too rich and good for you to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend; it ſhall produce its owne effect in power, and manifeſt your ungodlineſſe in contradicting of it: And know you, that no man ſhall appeare either directly or indirectly againſt it, but he ſhall by it diſcover the evill of his owne heart, and manifeſt that he walkes in darkneſſe, and knowes not the glorious counſell of the Lord.</p>
            <p>There is one place more I would have the world conſider, and it would make them afraid of judging: <hi>Math.</hi> 7.1, <hi>&amp;c. Judge not that you be not judged:</hi> You have judged the King and his party; for it you ſhall be judged, I'le judge you; <hi>And what judgement yee judge, you ſhall have; that meaſure that you give him you ſhall receive:</hi> You exclude him from peace, you have none your ſelves: You thruſt him from mercy, you have no mercy your ſelves: You live not in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of divine love, if you did, you could not be ſo cruell as you are, ſuch enemies to peace: You are that evill ſervant, God hath forgiven <hi>you ten thouſand talents,</hi> you come and take your fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſervant by the throat for <hi>an hundred pence:</hi> The Lord is wrath with you, and now your forgiveneſſe is recald, and you muſt pay the utmoſt farthing: You ſhall not have mercy, as you have had it, freely, but you ſhall ſuffer for it: You remember the Kings finnes, God will remember yours againe: Know this, you are not <hi>in the Kingdome of God, nor bleſſed;</hi> if you were, you would <hi>be peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers;</hi> for <hi>Bleſſed are the peace-makers, for theirs is the Kingdome of heaven;</hi> they that are bleſſed by the enjoyment of God, and in the light of Gods Kingdom they ſee all things in union, the King one with God; and the Parliament and people one with the King; they are one in God in his largeneſſe of love, but you are curſing, dividing, and ſo are in the Kingdome of darkneſſe and the Devill: This is your judgement, all the evill that you bring forth is within you; tis your owne, though you will fix it upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:116157:14"/>if it were not in you, you would not, could not produce it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And why beholdeſt thou the mote in thy brothers eye, but conſiderest not the beame that is in thine owne eye, &amp;c.</hi> The evils that you charge the King and his party with, though great in your narrow mindes, are but motes in the account of God; your ſmalneſſe aggravates them, his largeneſſe leſſens them; He that <hi>counts the nations as a drop of a bucket, and duſt of the ballance,</hi> counts theſe miſcarriages that are amongſt the nations a very ſmall matter, eaſily blowes away that which you ſilly creatures lift at as mountaines, toile and ſweat at it to bring forth ruine from it: Tis but a mote to a godly heart, eaſily forgiven; and a mote in the eye, hindring ſight; the King and his party many of them ſaw no better; thought they ought to defend their right againſt us that rebeld: And now its a more in the eye indeed, it vexes them they are afflicted for it under the hand of God, and thats your cruelty; <hi>You perſecute him whom the Lord hath finitten, and talke to the griefe of thoſe whom God hath wounded:</hi> But you have a beame in your eye: Your ſinnes are greater, being aggravated by many mercies, much light that others have not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed: your ſinne is a beame; your religion, ſtrength, upon which you leane and lay ſo much weight, thats become an iniquity, and a beame in your eye, that you cannot diſtinguiſh any thing, nor diſcerne good from evill, but are ſtarke blinde, you cannot ſee your brethren, but judge them enemies; and enemies are not fit judges: and if you could ſee them, brethren, you would not judg them as you doe; you cannot ſee to pull out the mote, to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the evill, and leave the eye, but you are pulling out the eye, the eye of the Kingdome, one that is the apple of Gods eye: of whom he fares, <hi>Touch it not:</hi> not the eye onely, but the head, and ſo the whole body, taking away the eye, that you may leade the body whether you pleaſe.</p>
            <p>Having taken this power of judging out of your hands, and ſhewd your ſinne and ſhame in preſuming upon it; We ſhall now conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſome grounds you lay downe why the King is not to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved againe to peace, nor reſtored to his office and dignity: And we ſhall in the view of them ſee how much your injuſtice is againſt God, and your ſelves, in that where you profeſſe for juſtice.</p>
            <p>Firſt, You inſiſt upon this, <hi>pag.</hi> 24. <hi>God hath given him ſo clearly in your hands to doe juſtice, and afterward God hath given a double judgement againſt him, &amp;c.</hi> And elſewhere you, pag. 5. to ſet forth Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116157:15"/>to you, you ſay, <hi>God makes haſt to judgement, and hath appeared as a ſevere avenger:</hi> Tis true, God hath judged the King againe and againe, and dealt very ſeverely with Him; He is the greateſt ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer in the Kingdome, having loſt His Crowne, Honour, Family, Liberty, Revenue, &amp;c. And you thrive, increaſe in wealth, honour, live better now then ever, are Lords where you come; and you add miſery to miſery, and affliction to affliction: Is this juſtice or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice? Hath God judged twice? And why will you not ſubmit to his judgement? Why will you take it out of Gods hand? Doth not God know how to doe it? Is he not ſevere enough? You ſay he is ſevere: Doth he want wiſedome to ſecure himſelfe and his people? He knowes not how to make all ſure, you muſt mend it: When did God chaſten or judge man, and then give him to men to chaſten againe? Or when did Gods people fall upon puniſhing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God had done it? Is God weary of afflicting, and repents him of the evill, or remiſſe in executing his judgement, that you would have men take it into their hands? Know, fooliſh men, your plea is your condemnation, and what you bring as your ſtrength, ſhewes your rebellion and unſubjection to the judgement of God</p>
            <p>Secondly, You argue, pag. 24. <hi>No remorſe appearing proportionable to the offence;</hi> if that could be ſeene, <hi>you ſhould regard it with a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable tenderneſſe towards him.</hi> Herein you deſtroy and deny that free mercy of God, upon which you have lived a long while; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that your profeſſion of the Goſpell was indeed but in letter, not in power; if it had, you would as freely <hi>forgive, as God for Chriſts ſake forgave you: And give freely as you have received freely.</hi> Where the love of God and the Goſpell comes in power, it transformes and changes the perſon into its owne glory, and makes a Chriſtian be indeed to others, what God is to him and in him. You requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>proportionable remorſe</hi> for the offence, and then will give <hi>propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable regard;</hi> how legall and humane is this? God forgives and ſhewes mercy, that men may repent; he loves firſt before we can love: but you muſt receive good before you can give, and will ſee repentance before grace, and that in the ſevereſt way of merit: Such ſure will be the way of God to you, yea, ſuch it, is, and your hearts are dry and utterly void of the riches of divine mercy; and you live upon your workes, duties, experience, victories, and ſuch empty huskes, and not upon the love of God; or elſe you would not bring forth ſuch wretched, harſh, flinty ſtuffe as this is.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:116157:15"/>
            <p>Then you ſay, <hi>There is no change of heart, no repentance, no free, nor full yeilding to all the parts of publique and religious intereſt:</hi> you know not the heart, nor can you judge of the Kings principles; they are too high for you, you know not your owne hearts, and therefore not his: you expect he ſhould turne, not to God, but to your forme of religion and government; and cannot count any thing a change, but yeilding to your way; which if he ſhould, he ſhould but be <hi>ſeven times more the Child of the Devill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tis true, the King hardly parts with his right, and unwilling to commit the government <hi>wholly</hi> into others hands; but he hath done it, though in weakneſſe and darkneſſe, in a ſmoke: but for you to quench this ſmoking flax, is not the ſpirit of Chriſt; he is in a doubting condition, 'tweene willingneſſe to yeild, and a feare of wronging himſelfe, his poſterity, and others by his grants; tis a hard caſe, and deſerves bowels of pity, and is pitied by the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of the mercy of God, though you deale harſhly with him. Its a hard thing to part with honour and greatneſſe; its eaſier far to ſeeke and get it then leave it: and if you could remember how God got ground in our hearts when he came to change us; how we diſputed every inch, &amp; never yeilded to the Lord but by conſtraint, you would accept of the Kings compliance: But remember, the <hi>ſame meaſure, &amp;c.</hi> you will have occaſion, ere long, to think of this with horror.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, You argue againſt the accommodation, becauſe now <hi>there is no equall ballance of affaires, pag.</hi> 24. Your meaning is, as you often expreſſe, the <hi>Kings forces are wholly ſubdued;</hi> he is in your pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and now <hi>to reſtore him to a ſtate of equality to your ſelves,</hi> making your ſelves levell with him.</p>
            <p>To all men yet; what you make an argument of ſeverity and juſtice, hath beene an argument of mercy: noble enemies require no more, but to get their enemies into their power, then they ſhew mercy, Tis <hi>Eliſha's</hi> reaſon concerning the <hi>Syrians, Wouldſt thou ſmite thoſe that thou haſt taken captive, with the ſword and with the born; ſet bread before them that they may eate and returne to their maſter.</hi> This way likewiſe the Father of mercies uſes and hath uſed to you and us, never bringing us downe, but that he might reſtore us and lift us up againe. And all noble creatures, both man and beaſt, have this part of the majeſty of God in them, to ſpare them they
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:116157:16"/>have ſubdued; only Devils get into their hands that they might torment.</p>
            <p>A fourth reaſon is, <hi>That he often cauſed warre to maintaine his intereſt againſt the publique intereſt, this conſtantly and unweariedly.</hi> We muſt note this by the way in propoſing ſuch an intereſt as you hold forth, to be the ground of the quarrell: you lye groſſely: for theſe things, as you propoſe them, were never thought on in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the quarrell; yea, the Parliament and we alwaies profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the contrary, &amp;c. never to alter the government; never to change the fundamentall lawes; yea, to protect and defend the Kings perſon: therefore the caſe now ſtated by you is much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from what it was; yea, theſe principles, you were lately not onely ignorant of them, but oppoſd them, when held forth by the Levellers; and are indeed but the duſt or ſhivers of a ſplit or broken Kingdome that you and they have gathered together to build your ſelves a neſt with, and taken up now in deſigne onely to attaine your end, malice, ambition and revenge.</p>
            <p>But your propoſing this as that againſt which the King made warre, you doe the moſt juſtifie the King that ever arty one did or can doe; for your preſent forme of government is ſuch a head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe monſter, ſuch a hoddy-doddy, ſuch an all-breech, ſo different from the majeſty of God, and the wifedome of men, that it would fright ſolid and ſerious men to their armes: if I ſhould fight againſt any thing I ſhould fight againſt this. And doth not your preſent practiſe confirme the King and his party in their way of warre, when they now ſee clearly, what before we conceald, that the life of the King and his poſterity is aimd at: If there be any reaſon for a Prince to take up armes againſt his ſubjects, this is, when men at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to deſtroy the King, and overthrow the very foundations of government: Tis true, for a Prince to ſtrip himſelfe wholly of all his dominion and royalty in love to his ſubjects, and to cure and recover their rebellions, is Chriſt-like; and the Lord will enable the King to make a full reſignation of all, and of Fife too, into the hands of God; and when he ſhall doe it, it will be his eaſe and deliverance: And what the Lord requires in light and mercy, you require in darkneſſe and malice; For the Lord takes away that he may reſtore againe; and the King ſhall by looſing ſave all; by parting, with his power unto God in darke and cruell men, ſhall receive it againe into the life and glory of God.</p>
            <p>You come, pag. 26. to the ſecond part of the queſtion, and a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:116157:16"/>reaſon againſt accommodation, <hi>The ſafety of this agreement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us conſider what you would have ſecured, and that is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in your Remonſtrance, That <hi>the King hath forfeited all his power into your hands;</hi> That <hi>the people are free to make the beſt advantages:</hi> And <hi>pag.</hi> 27. <hi>Having him and his party captivated, and in their power;</hi> and ſometimes you ſpeake, <hi>conqueſt;</hi> which ſhewes, that we have got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten all the King hath; we have, by warre, gotten advantage of power, honour, &amp;c. And this is in danger now to be given away and loſt by a Treaty; We ſee murder will out; what hath beene whiſpered in a corner, is come to be told upon the houſe top: We have all this while, to juſtifie our ſelves in this warre, ſaid, that our warre was but defenſive; and indeed if it prove otherwiſe, we muſt repent of it, and beare the ſhame of it; and now the truth ſhall come forth, I muſt deale plainly with you and my ſelfe; indeed its ſo groſſe in your writing, that it was not onely defenſive, but offenſive, that it cannot be conceald; and that we had deſignes of particular intereſt and advantage: When we began the war there was this in our mindes, and hath beene in our mindes continually, That the King and his party were wicked men, and not worthy or fit for their places and power they had; and that we were Saints, godly, and they did properly belong to us: That the Saints are to have the high places in the earth, and now was the time for theſe things to be performed, and no body is now fit to adminiſter juſtice, to rule over men, but we: Therefore we alwaies were glad of any of the Kings wayes that tended to difference and breach: glad when he left his Parliament and tooke armes, thinking that he was running to his deſtruction, and that he would ſplit himſelf and his party by it, and we ſhould have the ſpoile of them, and an opportunity to obtain our ends; and though we complaine now of the Kings obſtinacy, really we have beene alwaies glad of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it led to his deſtruction, and conſequently to our advantage; and the King not yeilding, you know, now at this time was thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after, and you would not ſtirre till he manifeſted a yeilding minde to accommodation, or peace; being alwaies held deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to our end, or the recovery of our right (the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) for we thinke our ſelves the onely true Lords: except the King would take part with us, and become one of our Saints, and ſo we ſhould ſhare with him. But wow God manifeſts that you are not Saints, but as weake men as others, as fooilſh, oppreſſing as others, if not worſe: that you are not in a condition of reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:116157:17"/>yet he is pleaſd to blaſt your honour and keep you low; and hath ſo ordered it, that a Treaty is on foot to ſettle things and you are left out, are likely to loſe thoſe places which you and your riend: have, &amp; not to attain thoſe golden daies you hoped to ſee: you find fancies of reigning to be but a dream that you muſt come down again from that you have gotten, and hoped to get; ſo your outward and fleſhly glory is dying, lies a bleeding in <hi>this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable inconvenience of a Treaty; this inſnaring Treaty;</hi> when you and your friends in the Houſe and abroad, ſhall have your hearts rip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped up to you, you'l ſay this is truth; and this is the reaſon that you ſeek ſecurity, ſomething to uphold your tottering Kingdom: Now to part with this is death to you, and you call it a <hi>prepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and ſelf-deſerting</hi> way, <hi>page</hi> 27. Now conſider this.</p>
            <p>Firſt, you have by this wofully defil'd your cauſe and manifeſt you undertooke the warre for advantage; though it may be you were ſuch ſtrangers to your owne hearts, as not to know it: But their is more evil in you then yet you underſtand, and it will break forth in your life. If the warre had been only defenſive, you would have reſted quietly, when much more is offered then we e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that you count all your own becauſe you have fought for it; the Kingdome and glory of it is but enough to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward you for your workes; that you have right to all, tis yours, and your parties, and this makes you often expreſſe the Kings title by conqueſt; indeed you would enforce him to hold by it, though he never mentiond it; becauſe its your <hi>preſent</hi> claim, you count your ſelves conquerours; which is a brutiſh thing, and by it you would extinguiſh civility, contract, religion, humane nature, law, and all the obligations of them to bring in your title, force: Beaſtly Warre: That you will loſe nothing, but keep what you have got, and would by warre and force ſecure what by force you have won; and therefore call <hi>ſelf-deſerting</hi> (all one with <hi>ſelf-deniing,</hi> or ſelf-for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking) <hi>prepoſterous</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now then to conclude this, you are not Saints yet; Saints will not ſeeke a Kingdome by the deſtruction of others, nor rejoice in the evill of others, either ſinne or puniſhment; not in others fall, that they may riſe; not advance themſelves by an Army compoſd of ungodly men; not by force, but love: Yet tis true, Saints ſhall reigne notwithſtanding, and thoſe will prove Saints before you, that you little thinke for; God <hi>will provoke you by a fooliſh people.</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:116157:17"/>Know too, that Saints rights are ſecure in heaven, and need not begge ſecurity of men; I ſcorne that cauſe that is ſubject to ruine and deſtruction; and therefore your feares and ſad expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of danger <hi>impending,</hi> ſhewes your foundation to be upon the ſands; <hi>I laugh at your deſtruction, and mocke when your feare comes:</hi> You live in God, ſtand for God, and the Goſpell of God, and talking of ruine and deſtruction; baſe is that way, and accurſed, that is ſubject to ſuch black thoughts; our cauſe is immortall, tis eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, it lives and triumphs in death, is gaine in loſſe, deſtruction is farre from us, we know it not: <hi>But ſit under our owne Vine and Fig tree, and none makes us afraid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another thing in danger, is, <hi>perſons engaged, the party adhering;</hi> you harpe often upon this ſtring, pag. 28, 29. foure or five times; you thinke the <hi>King will be revenged of you for your eminent activity against him:</hi> This diſcovers a baſe and poor ſpirit, and unbecoming Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſouldiers, to continue war, break off peace, deſigne the ruine of the King and his family, ſubvert the whole government of the Kingdome to ſecure your owne lives; and this, I know, is one maine reaſon of your preſent activity, and others are but aſſum'd and pretended to cover this; a Principle very deſtructive to a Kingdomes peace, and contrary to the ſpirit of Chriſt; <hi>fear, a ſnare and the pit have taken hold of you,</hi> that are forced t o continue the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance of a nation, and all the miſeries of warre upon us to ſave your ſelves: Let us ſuppoſe your feares (and the feares of thoſe that are called honeſt men, for this is a generall diſtemper) to be demonſtrations, as doubtleſſe to you they are, and that indeed the King ſhould picke out a dozen, or twenty, or more, to ſuffer; what then, ſuppoſe I were one of them, I account thus.</p>
            <p>I have victory over death, and death is ſwallowed up by victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and therefore cannot feare it, am free from it, death can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hurt me, I ſport with it, am above his reach; I live an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall life, and cannot ſee death; and he that hath not this free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is a ſlave.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I have no life but truth, and if truth be advanced by ſuffering, then my life alſo; if truth live, I live; if juſtice live, I live; and theſe cannot dye, but by any mans ſuffering are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, enthroned; and ſo I am enlarged: If I, or any other, have a life diſtinct from truth, its a lye; if diſtinct from juſtice, its un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:116157:18"/>
            <p>Thirdly, My life is a common life; I live with you and in you, I can confeſſe you and all have a right to it; if you come for it, take it; if I had a life ſeparated from you I would lay it downe for my brethren, and I ought to do it; that I might live with you, and you with me; <hi>and I would ſpoile principalities and powers by this croſſe;</hi> If the King ſhould come to take it, I would ſo freely yeild, that he could not but yeild to that love that can dye for him; &amp; ſo hold forth a true immortall power that is too ſtrong for earthly and fleſhly oppoſitions; or if any ſhould ſeeke my life, I would be content to give it, that I might live againe in their ſoules: And this is the way of the Goſpell to overcome Tyrants, and no other way, and to gaine Kingdomes indeed.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, I count it not an honeſt life that needs ſuch force with ſo much miſery to the Kingdome, to maintaine it; but on the other ſide I am engaged to dye for my Country, and I ſhall more advantage the cauſe of liberty and religion by one ſingle ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering that is pure, then we have done by all the bloud that hath beene ſhed in this rude way of warre; and lay a better and ſtronger foundation againſt tyranny and errour, then all theſe warres; I judge it ten times more honourable for a ſingle perſon, in witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing truth to oppoſe the world in its power, wiſdome and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ſtanding in its full ſtrength, and that nakedly and ſingly, then fighting many battels by army force; this Is brutiſh, common, the other Chriſtian, divine, holy, excellent; and therefore your great care of ſecuring your ſelves, comes from a ſlaviſh fear of death, from an unwillingneſſe to ſuffer, and want of the power of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe to meet the power of the world with, and true and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly love to your Country: you know not that command, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Walke in love as Chriſt alſo hath loved us, and hath given himſelfe a ſacrifice to God for a ſweet ſmelling ſavour:</hi> If you had this <hi>perfect love it would caſt out fear;</hi> if your life were indeed united to God, or <hi>Chriſt were your life,</hi> or that you loved others ſo as you could dye for them, you would not not now be to ſeeke for ſecurity: 'Tis your great fear, and expreſſed <hi>page</hi> 38. you may <hi>be made a ſacrifice:</hi> That which is propoſed to you by God, upon the example of Chriſt is abhord by you. If Chriſt had been led by this principle when he ſaw his enemies engaged againſt him to ſeeke his life, to have ſought their life to ſecure his own, he had not ſhewed himſelfe to be the Sonne of God: and you in this, declare your ſelves not to be the Sonnes of God: It's no juſtice, leſſe piety, to take away a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116157:18"/>life to ſave our owne; that's the way of God to lay down his life for others: and thats a wicked life that requires other mens lives to maintain it, that cannot ſtand but by others fall.</p>
            <p>Now let us conſider the reaſons of the inſecurity of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like intereſt in this accomodation; you give many, and may give many more, considering how much wrath God hath let out upon the world and all parts of it to deſtroy it; 'tis the eaſieſt thing now that can be to finde out wayes of ruine; but hard to finde wayes of peace: and though we muſt confeſſe you very quick-ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in diſcovering of dangers, and very ſenſible of evil, yet we wil not admire it as any excellent piece of policy, but judge it as the effect of a fearful and ſelf-condemning ſpirit.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, you fall downe into the obſervation of paſt times, and <hi>challenge ſtory for an inſtance &amp;c. page</hi> 27. There is, I know, a good uſe of ſtory; but in you, it is a dul and heterogene ous thing; and a looking back for ſtrength, declining your owne principles which you have profeſſed; new light, the Kingdome of Chriſt, to be carried on by the Spirit and power of God; and thoſe things will not, you know; ſubject themſelves to the weakneſſe and darknes of former ages: you know you have a light of truth and juſtice that no age can paralel; that your waies are beyond all example: why doe you then diſturb the dead, and challenge them to teſtify in theſe affairs that they are ignorant of? <hi>Or why doe you ſeek the living amongſt the dead,</hi> and depart from the living God to dead Idols to relieve you?</p>
            <p>Then you bring forth many <hi>evill ſurmiſings,</hi> as <hi>how apt Princes are to break ſuch accommodations, and how eaſy tis for them;</hi> page 29. and in proving theſe, <hi>you are as a bird wandring from her neſt, you have forgotten your resting place,</hi> and being in a darke wilderneſſe, you are purſued by fear and wrath on every ſide; I will not follow you in you wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derings; but give you ſight of your condition in theſe few obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, You looke upon all paſt paſſages and preſent actions in this Kingdome, in the darkneſſe of man, not in the light of God; in the weakneſſe, inſtability and unfaithfulneſſe of wicked man; not in the ſtrength, ſtability and faithfulneſſe of a righteous God.</p>
            <p>If you would ſee the peace of God in this agreement (though covered with rags) you would rejoyce in it and bleſſe it; and if
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:116157:19"/>you ſaw God bringing down wicked powers, and preventing of them in an evil courſe, you would reſt in the worke of the Lord, and know God that hath done it is faithfull, and wil doe it ſtill. If you ſaw the juſtice of God againſt tyranny and oppreſſion, you would know that, juſtice is eternal and will for ever ſecure us: or if you ſaw God give us theſe conceſſions and grants from the King; God diſpoſing his heart by fear or love, and could ſay 'tis the Lord that doth it, you might think he will continue them to us, or if he take them away 'tis to give us better: If you did ſee <hi>the heart of the King is in the hand of the Lord,</hi> and 'tis by him he yeelds to what he yeelds; you would reſt in it, that the ſame hand will cauſe him to doe more: or if you ſaw God hath taken the King into his power, and ſo the whole Nation; that God hath taken his great Reign, the power of God is come forth to ſway the Scepter, then you would conclude that Satan ſhall not miſleade the King to be treacherous and falſe to us: But you behold things as they are in the wicked one, and there you finde nothing but curſes, feares, troubles; and it's beſt for you that you might by that be led to the Lord: But for the preſent you ſee things onely in a carnall eye, and not with a ſpiritual, and ſo with an evil eye, which is the reaſon you cannot ſee your rock, the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, You doe declare, by your fears, and expreſly by words, that thoſe things that the Parliament now obtains of the King, in the way you behold them, that they are forced things, not natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, but violent, and ſo not durable: that they are unjuſt and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing, and ſo not laſting: for if you could looke upon them as naturall, or right and juſt, you had reaſon to think they were laſting; for God is the protector of juſt things, and ſtand firm a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the power of hel; and if they were ſo in you and them, or as far as they are ſo, all things that appeare againſt them will be daſht in pieces, Juſtice being an invincible Rock: but you are extreame ſenſible of their going back againe to the King from whence they came; and returning to their origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</p>
            <p>If you did indeed believe that the originall of power were in the People, theſe grants would reſt with you; and if there be any more behinde, you might be perſwaded they would freely follow theſe you have already, for things naturally or by the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:116157:19"/>of God run to their center. But it ſeems you finde no peace in theſe, and complain of the danger you are in of loſing of them, which ſhews thoſe things have no good bottome or foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in you: And know this, that theſe violent courſes that you are upon, of <hi>diſclaiming and renouncing all dependance on the King, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord with him, and an utter rejection, expulſion and depoſure either of his whole race, and all that claim it upon the ſame account of right; or at leaſt of his particular Perſon, and execution of juſtice upon him, page</hi> 28. wil not ſecure what you have got; but rather it is the way to loſe them, and ſet up Princes in a higher way then ever: for all things being by force, compelled from their nature, that force being removed, they returne with the greater earneſtneſſe: and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is violent can be perpetuall: Beſides, <hi>Hee that will ſave his life ſhall loſe it:</hi> eſpecially when it is going, and men uſe wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed waies to uphold their tottering ſtate, then it goes, as wee ſay, with a vengeance; and that is your condition: God ſayes in your hearts and conſciences, your ſtanding is corrupt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, and he hath a quarrel againſt it, and it muſt fall: The rumour of your fall (In reſpect of your preſent greatneſſe) ſounds in your boſomes, and it is that which puts you up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe courſes to ſave your ſelves, which will haſten your fall.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Your deep ſenſe that you have of the Kings <hi>recovering what he hath loſt, of his getting into his ſeat and Throne again, and of the diſpoſition of the generallity of people to help him to his beloved dignity:</hi> whence you make ſuch totall concluſions <hi>not onely of probabilities of danger, but certain inſecurity, and perpetuall prejudice to publi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e intereſt, ſuppoſd the beſt conſtitutions and ſtricteſt laws imaginable &amp;c. page</hi> 47. Theſe things doe declare that theſe Conceſſions are not long lived; and doe propheſie the reſtitution of the King to his ancient Rights, and give a clear teſtimony to the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality and ſtability of Kinglines.</p>
            <p>You ſee that the King hath a will to redeeme his preſent loſſe: you may ſee it in your owne hearts, that every man hath a luſt after power and authority: And you have ſeene it in his conſtant carriage. For my part I condemne his unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeeking of it, and any falſhood in it, but if he ſhould not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour the maintaining: and reſtoring of the dignity of Kings, Hee were falſe to his truſt, and the glory and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of God that he is intruſted with: And therefore
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:116157:20"/>that deſire of recovering his loſſe, is juſtifiable in him; yea, I ſhould condemne him as unbelieving and weake ſpirited, if he ſhould not hope for it, and conſtantly aime at it: But here's his miſery, and yours for the preſent, that you are not acquainted with that ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of power that is in God to diſpenſe, and that wiſdom where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it ſhall be diſpoſd; ſo that he ſhall have as much and more then ever he had, and you all, and more then you deſire; and that way will be ſhewed him to confirme what you aske of him, and give you more, and yet continue his owne Royalty in the greateſt abſo luteneſſe and perfection: And for want of this, you are tug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and pulling the Kingdome in peices to ſatisfie your ſelves with dominion; whereas if you were in a right underſtanding of things, there is enough in God, in the nation, to ſatisfie all deſires, and largeneſſe enough for all to have what they would, without entrenching one upon another, or maligning one another. If he deſire it in a carnall and wicked way, he ſhall never have it; If he commit it to the Lord, and expect, it from him, he ſhall have it, and that will be his and our mercy.</p>
            <p>Tis granted then, that he hath a minde to recover, and that this is according to his principle, and maybe managed rightly, and not to the prejudice of the Parliament, or his oppoſers: And that he ſhall riſe, yea, is now great, your Remonſtrance ſeales to it. You condemne the Parliament for owning him ſo farre, as to ſeeke to him by a Treaty; and you by taking ſuch paines to arme your ſelves againſt him, make it manifeſt, he hath a great power; which is a wonder, that a Prince, ſpoild of all his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, naked, a priſoner, deſtitute of all friends and helps, whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the diſpoſe of others, tied and bound with all obligations a that a Parliament can imagine to hold him, ſhould yet be ſuch terrour to you, and fright you into ſuch a large Remonſtrance, and ſuch perilous proceedings as you are upon to ſave your ſelves from him, that is now a worme; either you are full of fear, that are ſo affected with a ſhadow, or elſe there is ſome ſtrange power in him.</p>
            <p>As you give teſtimony to his power, ſo you take a courſe to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance it; for there is nothing that hath any ſparke of God in it, but the more it is ſuppreſid, the more it riſes; afflictions being alwaies great improvements to good things, which ſhine moſt when they are tried.</p>
            <p>You ſpeake of his reputation, pag. 36. The more you cruſh
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:116157:20"/>him, the ſweeter ſavour comes from him; and while he ſuffers, the Spirit of God and glory reſt upon him: There is a ſweet glory ſparkling in him by ſuffering though you ſee it not: You do but rend away his corruptions from him, and help to waſt his droſſe, and draw forth that hidden excellency that is in him; and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally men are ready to pity ſufferers, When nothing will gaine me, affliction will; I confeſſe his ſufferings make me a Royaliſt, that never cared for him: He that doth and can ſuffer ſhall have my heart; you had it while you ſuffered; now you are great, and need it not; the poore, ſuffering, oppreſſed King and his party ſhall have my compaſſion; your ſevere puniſhing him for his weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in government, and great abuſe of government your ſelves, will beget in people an high account of the King, and provoke them to greater rage againſt you; and therefore you are upon fooliſh waies; while you, are ſeeking to prevent theſe evils, you are running further into them; you are raiſing more evils againſt your ſelves, not allaying of them: Tis the power of love binds men from hurting you; cruelty inrages men, and will turne men into Devils againſt you.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Your ſpeech ſhewes what's within, <hi>Out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh: A good man, out of the good treaſure of his heart, bringeth forth good things; and an evill man, out of the evill treaſure of his heart, bringeth forth evill things:</hi> no man can ſpeake any thing but himſelfe. Tis our happineſſe to live to ſee the hearts of men clearly brought forth.</p>
            <p>You tell us of the King, how probable, yea, demonſtrable tis, that he will caſt off <hi>theſe verball and literall confeſſions and conceſſions, and that his yeilding for the preſent is but upon deſigne to obtaine the Throne, but when be hath it hee'l quickly breake, and have colourable grounds for it:</hi> Which doth but tell us what you would doe, or what is in your hearts to doe: It ſeemes you are able to teach the King deceit, and to ſhew him a way to eſcape out of all engagements; <hi>Charity think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no evill,</hi> becauſe it thinks nothing but God, <hi>it hopes all things, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves</hi> all things, becauſe it ſees God at the bottom of all things: But you hope for nothing but deceite, falſhood and treachery, <hi>Wiſe to doe evill, but to doe good no knowledge:</hi> You ſpeake evill, but cannot ſgeake good; Curſe you doe, but bleſſe not; you never ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good of the King, or any, but in ſcorne; and ſo you mention the King (Good man) So <hi>large</hi> and <hi>cunning</hi> in diſcovery of <hi>ill,</hi> and void of <hi>good,</hi> ſhewes you empty of one, and full of the other.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:116157:21"/>
            <p>Fifthly, You expreſſe a multitude of dangers ready to come upon us by this Treaty; from the King his <hi>reputation, party their multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,</hi> their <hi>activity,</hi> their <hi>greatneſſe,</hi> from <hi>abroad,</hi> from <hi>home, from the Parliament their diviſions, their burdening the people with taxes, from the force that is upon the King, &amp;c. Feare hath taken bold of you,</hi> it en com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes you about on every ſide; Like <hi>Cain,</hi> that ſaies. <hi>Every one that meeteth me will kill me;</hi> you know no ſafety: Can this be away of God? Doth not <hi>God eſtabliſh our goings, and ſet our feet upon a rock,</hi> and make us able to <hi>lye downe and ſleepe in a wilderneſſe,</hi> and not be afraid? We know none can hurt us, having <hi>Salvation for wals and bulwarkes,</hi> and can and doe live in the face of hell, death, Devils, and not be diſturbed, yea, ſeeke no other protection then the arme of God.</p>
            <p>They <hi>are the ſinners in Sion that are afraid;</hi> We that are the people of God, dwell in that mountaine where there is no hurtfull thing; <hi>Our City gates ſtand open night and day,</hi> and we feare no ſurprizes, no deſignes can betray us; we are not troubled to ſhut our gates to keepe out death, <hi>evill flyes from us;</hi> we need no black deſigns againſt our enemies to ſave our ſelves, we do declare againſt all that walk in a way contrary to this; <hi>That their wiſdom is not from above, not pure, ſo not peaceable, but is earthly, carnally ſenſuall and deviliſh.</hi> In this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed ſtate you are in, is ſeene your judgement is begun; you have left God, and he hath left you to theſe tormenting feares; this is the wrath that was threatned upon you; you are ſeeking ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafety, tis your buſineſſe; therefore you uphold your Army to preſerve the lives of the godly party, and ſafety flyes from you: God lookes every way upon you with ſadneſſe and wrath; tis your wickedneſſe to thinke of, or ſpeake of ſafety in a worldly ſtate; you have beene taught otherwiſe, and know, you ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have it; you thinke you may uſe the meanes, no, all meanes are wicked that have an end contrary to the revealed will of God; and this hath beene told your hearts, that there's no peace but in God. This is a generall diſtemper, and that which your friends are guilty of extreamly, but <hi>Tis the ſpirit of hondage to feare, and not of love and a ſound minde.</hi> This paſſion ſets you on work, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your buſineſſe muſt needs be baſe and vile; to act for ones ſelfe in any kinde, is evill and un-chriſtian; but to aft for ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafety is ſo meane and poore a thing, as it muſt needs produce moſt vile and abſurd actions: It is of all affections the unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt; a deepe pit, and cauſes blacke, horrid and foule things: I'le ſhew you a little that reſt and peace which we enjoy; that ſecurity
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:116157:21"/>which you have turned your backes upon, in refuſing the Lord, and for want of it are groping in theſe darke waves of yours.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I feare no party nor intereſt becauſe I love all, I am recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to all, and all are reconciled to me; I have enmity to none but the <hi>ſon of perdition;</hi> I oppoſe nothing but deſtruction, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nothing oppoſes me: Tis enmity begets inſecurity; and while men live in the fleſh, and in enmity to any party or intereſt, in a privace, divided and ſelfe good, there will be perpetuall wars and ſtrife; except that particular ſhould quite ruine all other parts, and live alone, which the univerſall muſt not, will not ſuffer, for the admitting a part to eate up and devoure others, were to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the whole, which is God; and ſuch a minde in any part doth not onely fight with another part, but againſt the whole; and ſo every faction of men ſtriving to make themſelves abſolute, do di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly warre againſt God, who is love, peace, and a generall good, gives being to all, and cheriſhes all; and therefore in ſuch, oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of fellow members, and of God, the God of peace and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there can be no peace nor ſecuricy: But we being enlarged in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the largeneſſe of God, and comprehending all things in our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes by the divine ſpirit, are at reſt with all, and delight in all, for we know nothing but what's in our hearts; Kings, Nobles are much beloved becauſe they are in us, of us, one with us, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Kings and Lords by the anointing of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>We inherit all things, having overcome;</hi> we are free the Sons of God, and all things are given unto us, are our owne for our uſe: the greateſt as well as the leaſt; and therefore feare no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, being Lords of all: To be in a ſtate apprehenſive of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is to be a ſervant; and while ſervants are quarrelling one with another, beating one another, their Lord is abſent, and they are in danger one of another.</p>
            <p>This is the condition of all the world, and of you in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and therefore are farre from Lordſhip, true ſpirituall reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; yea, hell, deaths deſtruction it ſelfe is ours, and doth us ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: <hi>In our great houſes there are veſſels of honour and of diſhonour;</hi> both uſefull and profitable; Captivity is become our captive; death is become life; confuſion hath its beauty, they are all excellent, as wee in our houſe diſpoſe of them and enjoy them; our
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:116157:22"/>intereſt is publique, extends to all, and all are our intereſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>We live in heaven, peace is in our wals, and plenty, in our pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;</hi> that word is performed to us, <hi>They ſhall ſee evill no more;</hi> wee know no evill in our <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> not eating of the <hi>forbidden fruit;</hi> all is good, in all we ſee a ſmiling, bright, ſweet face of majeſty; Wee live upon Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> and it is large enough to receive our ſouls, bodies, eſtates, lives, families, all is taken within the Gates of the Holy City, and this City reaches all over the earth: Here we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy all things, all perſons, all actions, we never goe out of it, but live in the peace and ſafety of it continually: And here there is <hi>no more curſe, nor death, ſorrow and ſighing flee from us; God wipes all tears from our eyes,</hi> and enjoying this, and all in this, in truth and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; we need no defence, no ſafety but our owne rocke. <hi>Our houſe which is from heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, I feare nothing in the world, becauſe <hi>Greater is he that is in us, then he that is in the world; I have overcome the world, it is at my feet, I trample upon it;</hi> If you finde any world in me, you ſhall doe me right to afflict it, break it; Let it ſuffer, tis righteous it ſhould, I would have no worldly thing that lives out of God have reſt, its againſt my life and principle; and by this I doe overcome it, and ſhall never be troubled for the loſſe of it, for I would have no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, no life or being but in the eternall world: The world, I know, it is a poore ſhadow, a fading thing, and is onely terrible in the darke, theres nothing in it, but it is more excellently and mightily in us in God; Men, Kings, Emperours, as they are in an earthly ſtate, we know they are wormes that ſhall dye, mortals, and trouble they may themſelves, not us; They are not worthy of a caution to them that live above them, or take heed: Have they power: ſo have we everlaſting power, and either theirs is one with ours, or infinitely ſhort of it: you ſhew your ſelves weake and under them when you feare them. Have they policy, wiſedome, we have treaſures; either theirs is ours, or elſe we can make fooles of them; if they act not in our light, we are, and can, when we will, goe beyond them; they are filly men that fear cunning, nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row pated men, that cannot ſecure themſelves from policy: Have they multitudes, a large and numerous party; we have more, and they can have none but ours, all are ours, we have <hi>Legions, ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times ten thouſand; They that are with us are more then they that are againſt us;</hi> yea, all are for us, if they knew us and what they would have, we having with us the <hi>deſire of all nations:</hi> Would they have a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:116157:22"/>King, they are in the darke; but wee know they truly can deſire none but our King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and if you doubt and fear, you are ſolitary and alone, a widow, not married to God and his innumerable hoſts: Of all things we would not fear men becauſe they are wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, falſe, breakers of Covenant, perfidious, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is to <hi>ſet up wickedneſſe by a Law;</hi> to accuſe God, that the wicked goe unpuniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that 'tis in vain to ſerve him, that he is not juſt; 'tis to offer the higheſt honour to the baſeſt creatures, men in wickednes; We know they worke in that fire that will deſtroy them: if men be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil they can't hurt me but as they hurt themſelves; they are haſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to their own deſtruction, they carry their ruine with them: beſides, we know ſuch men are in hel, and there chaine them: though Kings; we can, by the power of God, binde them in chains of Iron: have power to binde the devil and caſt him into the bottomleſſe pit: We aſſure you, that the devil ſhal not appear in any form or perſons, be they never ſo great, never ſo gifted, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo glorious in religion or power, be it in you or any other, but we will deal with him, caſt loads of wrath upon him, and fil him with torment; caſt him from his heaven of outward religion or power, and ſecure him within his own bounds, that he ſhall no longer deſtroy the earth: We doe and wil diſſolve his works be they never ſo wiſely contrived, <hi>Set our feet upon him, and tread upon this Lyon and Adder,</hi> and he ſhall not hurt us.</p>
            <p>Therefore you, while you tel us or your <hi>great fears,</hi> and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate certain <hi>certain inſecurity,</hi> and travel to bring forth your ſenſe of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, you and the godly party are in; you think you are wiſe men, muſt act as rational men for your ſafety, and judge us fools, mad men, that if you ſhould doe as wee, the whole Chriſtian cauſe would fall to the ground, and all would be loſt; We wil lay this upon you, <hi>Rev:</hi> 21.8. <hi>The fearfull and unbelieving &amp;c, have their part in the lake which burneth with fire and brimſtone, which is the ſecond death:</hi> you are in a lake of ſire, <hi>worke in the fire,</hi> and <hi>this is of the Lord,</hi> it is the juſt judgement of God upon you; not of men, but of and by the Lord; you are beyond the reach of men, but are reſerved to be puniſht, from the preſence of the Lord, <hi>This is your ſecond death;</hi> you were dead in ſinnes, are quickned by repentance, but are gone back; the life of grace and Religion is dead in you, and you that eſcaped the firſt, are fallen into a ſecond death: But one word more anſwering to this, <hi>Revelations</hi> 22.15. <hi>Without are dogges:</hi> you are acting all along <hi>without the City:</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:116157:23"/>yea, profeſſedly ſetting up a power that is in the world at diſtance from and out of God; which you cal <hi>higheſt power on earth, created, ſtanding power on earth;</hi> and for <hi>that power that divinity hath deſign'd,</hi> you laugh at it; &amp; you know your <hi>wholl trade</hi> is <hi>now</hi> driven in the world as diſtinct from heavenly things, though you would cover it too with a ſheeps skin, and cry tis the Lord, the Lord with us: but you are caſt out, and gone out, and live out of the bleſſed and glorious preſence of God, and ſo are <hi>dogs</hi> rated by God into a filthy kennel of baſe things; and are fearful as <hi>dogs:</hi> God hath beaten you by the King, and kept you under, and you are fearful of the ſame hand ſtil, and thinke 'twill be worſe yet, we ſhall ſuffer again; and that ſets you a barking out your wrathful angry and feirce ſtuffe. If you were with your Father in his preſence as Sonnes, theſe cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours would ceaſe, and you would be above all, and doe good to all, and bleſſe all as your Father doth.</p>
            <p>This is a main ground-worke of your whole buſines; that law of nature which teaches men to ſave themſelves, and therefore wee have taken the more paines to diſcover the rottenneſſe of it, and how you decline God and grace to flye to depraved and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature to be your guid and God; and to the poore and baſeſt principle of nature, ſelf-preſervation, which muſt lead to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthieſt things; and for profeſſed Chriſtians to act ſo low, is great wickednes and a curſe.</p>
            <p>You doe in this diſcourſe meet with two objections.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Your own former declaring for the King, which ſeems a little to trouble you; but you with ſome difficulty ſcramble over it; and I thinke in that ſpirit that you are in will ſtand at nothing: we will only ſay this, that by breaking thoſe Propoſals, you juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy all the breach of promiſe in the King or any others, and doe, not onely <hi>break the command, but teach men to doe ſo;</hi> for upon the principles of your apology for your ſelves, every man is free from all engagements whatſoever.</p>
            <p>As firſt, you ſay, <hi>page.</hi> 43. concerning your complyance with the King, <hi>Partly neceſſitating us for the preſent prevention of that miſchiefe to the publike they were runing into in that kinde as we apprehended: we were drawn into &amp;c.</hi> if men for <hi>neceſſity,</hi> and to avoid <hi>publique danger,</hi> ſay a thing though hee performe it not, there is no great evil in it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That <hi>moderation was but Hypotheticall;</hi> That is
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:116157:23"/>no ſuch engagements are abſolute, but conditionall, nor to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, but ſaving the Publique intereſt; Now we being judges of what is ſafe for the publique intereſt, can deliver our ſelves when we pleaſe; which is the <hi>Phariſees law, If a man ſay it is Corban, its a gift, ſhall be free.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>We aimd not at the ſtrengthening our ſelves to the ruin of any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but to prevent, &amp;c.</hi> So that there be honeſt intentions, we may ſteppe over theſe outward bonds; and wiſely to prevent miſchief, breake all relations, trample upon all authority. And afterward you repent, and ſay, <hi>'Twas errour, frailty, unbeliefe and carnall counſels,</hi> pag. 44. And pag. 52. you fall upon it againe, and there you ſay were led to it by the Parliaments courſe: and now God hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened your eyes, <hi>and let you ſee beyond what you did before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How excellently doe you teach men to goe from what they have ſaid; if they ſee further and can repent it, they are free: See how abhominable religion is when once corrupted: Theres no kinde of men can be ſuch compleat and neat knaves, as a Jeſuite, a Phariſee, an old well ſtudied profeſſour of Religion; when once mens conſciences are defiled, and they begin to trade in the world, with a pretence that tis for God, they are ſo cunning, that no bonds of honeſty or faith can poſſibly hold them.</p>
            <p>This buſineſſe of your repentings concerning your former com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with the King, is a great ſtrength to you, and you much build upon it: You have ſeene your ſinne, you ſay, and been hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for it, and ſought God, and are cleane from it, you have been troubled, but now are at peace: Alas poore men! <hi>A deceived heart hath turned you aſide, and you ſee not the lye in your right hand; This your Righteouſneſſe is a broken bow that ſtarts aſide; A broken reed, that while you leane upon it, will peirce your hand.</hi> To ſhame you for the iniquity of holy things, and ſhew the abhomination even of your Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, Know this from him who knowes your wayes and hearts.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That it was not your ſinne to carry out principles of <hi>ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe and goodneſſe</hi> to all, and of faire and gentle dealing towards enemies, as you formerly did in your propoſals: but to doe this falſly and hypocritically, to take theſe <hi>Lambe-like</hi> propoſals to cover a <hi>Ravening Wolfe;</hi> or to aſſume them, not out of love to them, but to gaine reputation; or to gull and cheate a party into a quiet waiting upon you for deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:116157:24"/>till you had gaind your end, and then deceive them, and wholly relinguiſh them, this is your ſinne; And this you were by me admoniſhed of concerning the King, that if you did looke towards him, you ſhould nakedly and freely diſcover your hearts and boſomes to him; if he did ſo cloſe with you, it might be wel; but that you ſhould not (as you did) in diſtruſt of God, falſly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out judgement accept of him and agree with him, that was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to you to be evill, and a <hi>daubing with untempered morter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, In your turning now you turne not to God; God ſaies to you, <hi>You do not at all faſt to me, but you are an empty vine bringing forth fruit to your ſelves:</hi> For this preſent expedition, though you are blinde and ſee it not, is meerly for and to your ſelves; And there are in you the ſame wickedneſſe that was in the former, and worſe; <hi>frailty</hi> is now malice; <hi>unbeliefe</hi> turnd to ſelf-confidence; <hi>carnall counſell</hi> into deviliſh counſell: There is nothing more of the glory of God in you now, but leſſe; yea, <hi>That which you ſeem'd then to have is taken from you;</hi> your wiſedome, mercy, moderation, &amp;c. So you turne not from the iniquity of your way; not from this in hypocirſy, to this in truth, in righteouſneſſe; but from a vaine propoſall of good to acting evill, you turne indeed, but to <hi>Egypt,</hi> you are gone from good in ſhew, to evill in ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The root of this worke you have in hand is a ſenſe of the loſſe of Gods favour; you have felt Gods frownes upon you, and that hath put you upon this work, to recover your loſt ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, and to make ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>This is a miſerable, dark principle, and begets very wicked pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes: in a ſenſe of the wrath of God to ſeek for means to expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate his diſpleaſure: <hi>Eſavs</hi> teares, <hi>Sauls</hi> ſacrificing, <hi>Iſraels</hi> offering up <hi>the firſt borne of their bodies for the ſinne of their ſoules:</hi> Poore blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men! when they ſeeke to ſatisfie God, run more in wickedneſſe againſt him: he that goeth upon ſuch grounds to ſatisfie an angry God, and to quiet a fearfull and guilty conſcience, will alwaies be bloudy and cruell, and are thruſt on commonly to ſome eminent folly, ſome notorious and abſurd wickedneſſe, and ſo are you, not being eſtabliſht in the love of God, nor walking in a <hi>plaine path of righteouſneſſe,</hi> but blinded in wrath, are hurried from one extream to another: This curſed giddineſſe of fleſh to doe evill, and think they doe <hi>God good ſervice,</hi> is the fruit of apoſtacy, and <hi>quenching the ſpirit of God;</hi> to be ſo left to your ſelves, that which way ſoever you goe, you commit iniquity, and not able to know or practiſe the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:116157:24"/>truth; you are in this the greateſt examples of divine juſtice that this age hath brought forth.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing that lies in your way, is the <hi>Covenant,</hi> which <hi>obliges to the preſervation of the Kings perſon and authority, pag.</hi> 54. but not ſo ſtrongly, but <hi>the ſnare is broken, and you have an honeſt way to eſcape;</hi> Many things you bring to quit your ſelves from it; that clauſe, <hi>In the preſervation of the true Religion and liberty of the Kingdome, pag.</hi> 55. <hi>If it have an evill ſenſe it cals for repentance, pag.</hi> 57. This how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever will never faile, repentance knowes how to waſh away any Covenant. Then you plead, 'twas 'twixt <hi>man and man,</hi> and would exclude the King, <hi>as not preſent nor conſenting, pap.</hi> 58. and after would exclude God from being any thing but <hi>a witneſſe, pag.</hi> 50. You would have God have as little intereſt in it as you can: Tis a very ill tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of minde that leſſens the intereſt of God in our affaires: Its an ill tongue that is an oratour for man, and denies God; that ſaies God <hi>is but thus:</hi> Tis no diſhonour to the King to be left out, where God is not admitted to be a party, onely a looker on: But God ſaies, <hi>What you did to one of theſe little ones, you did to me:</hi> You vowd to me in the King, though a little one, impriſoned, ſicke, naked; yet your oath was to me.</p>
            <p>God ſaies, I put in the preſervation of the Kings life and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority into the Covenant, into all your oaths and proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, on purpoſe to ſave him after all his ſufferings for ſin: And ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance is due to me; I was in that Covenant, and will puniſh the breakers: Where are you now?</p>
            <p>Concerning your breaking this Covenant in a thing ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, ſo agreeable to all the Parliaments Declarations and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrances, we will lay downe theſe three conſiderations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That Oaths and Covenants, the maine pillars of humane ſociety, the greateſt determiners of controverſies, the chiefe part of divine worſhip, is in this age moſt commonly violated, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently prophaned: Poore world! what will you doe? Thy great ſecurity from danger, Oaths, thy Phyſitian that hath cured thy breaches often, and heald diſtempers, is become ineffectuall: There is ſuch wickedneſſe amongſt us, and that crept into the beſt of men, and under ſuch pretences of piety to God, that no Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants will hold them: Certainly if God doth not manifeſt, <hi>a new and everlaſting Covenant</hi> to compoſe and binde us together, we ſhall live in a wilderneſſe of horrid confuſion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That theſe are the laſt and perilous times ſpoken of,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:116157:25"/>2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. &amp;c. And that you, amongſt others, are the people there ſpoken of, <hi>Lovers of themſelves;</hi> That's your <hi>fundamentall Law, ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſervation,</hi> and the ground of your preſent actings, to intrude your ſelves into the worlds greatneſſe, out of a high opinion of your owne deſerts, thinking your ſelves onely wiſe, juſt, holy, honourable, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I could ſhew you the other particulars, and may in time apply the Text to you, if you repent not; but for the preſent occaſion, tis ſaid, there they ſhall be <hi>Truce-breakers,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, againſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation, no treaty, no agreement: Or breakers of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and then it followes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Accuſers,</hi> and at this you are exquiſite.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That Covenants being the ſtrength of humane ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and ſo great bulwarks of the world, degenerated or apoſtaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Religion is the great engine of Gods wrath appointed to breake them downe: Solemne Oaths and Covenants are able to hold moſt mens conſciences, but men heightned by Religion into the forms of the ſpirit, doing things by immediate direction from God, carrying a glorious preſence of God before them, affirming that they are called by God to doe ſome ſpeciall worke in the world: theſe can eaſily mount above the higheſt forts of Oaths, and trample them under foot preſently: Men that have taſted of theſe high things, and begin to make them ſerviceable to worldly ends, they are ſuch cunning pick-locks, that they can finde a way through all dores to come to the treaſures of power and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: A people that have had a ſavour of heavenly things in a fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way: turne them looſe into the world, and they'l teare it up by the roots; they are whetted for deſtructions ſuch as are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 21.31. <hi>Brutiſh men, skilfull to destroy:</hi> ſuch wicked ſpirits are now abroad, that are <hi>brutiſh,</hi> ſpare not the holieſt nor honourableſt things: Kings, Lords, Miniſters, Scriptures, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, Oaths, Covenants lay all waſte; and yet in the greateſt brutiſhineſſe, <hi>skilfull,</hi> though there be the moſt ſenſuall and beaſtly confuſion, yet they ſhall doe it artificially, <hi>skilfully,</hi> ſay tis for God, juſtice, religion, &amp;c. and that they doe it by the power of Chriſt, and the ſpirit of God, in religious zeale, &amp;c. and ſo exact, that they will not be knowne from builders, reſtorers, reformers. But the holy, good, wiſe, mercifull ſpirit of the living God, the Father of mercies, will in his owne light condemne this <hi>uncleane ſpirit, and drive him out of the land.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:116157:25"/>
            <p>Having <hi>cleared your way to what you have to propoſe you give us your apprehenſions of the remedy, page</hi> 60. your firſt is <hi>to, lay aſide this evil and dangerous Treaty:</hi> This is a ſtrange remedy againſt civil warres, to lay aſide treating: Then you require <hi>that the Kings demands be rejected, eſpecially that of his reſtitution to</hi> London; This is very terrible to you that the King ſhould recover any ſtrength; no, keepe him downe as long as you can, let him not riſe: how far is this from the power of godlines, oracting in the power of God: a poore puſilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous, cowardly, worldly policy: you dare not thinke of the King getting any power, for then you know you durſt not deale with him; not barely in the power of God: but he a priſoner and you free; having an Army at your command, you dare accuſe him; if he were in power, you would ſhrinke out of the Kingdome; whereas if you lived in the power of God, you might trample up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Thrones; if he were wicked pul him from his greateſt glory, and binde him in chains.</p>
            <p>Secondly, you would <hi>have that bargaining propoſition laid aſide, and would have all juſtice done immediatly, from the judiciall power of the Kingdome the Parliament, and not by grant from the King:</hi> you doe the King a courteſy in that: and this being done, <hi>you wiſh moderation and mercy;</hi> not as long as there be any apprehenſion of fear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there's little mercy from fearful enemies: mercy is in Breaſts that are ſtrong and mighty. But <hi>page</hi> 62. you come to the marrow of the buſineſſe, to propound high things that ſha1l reach <hi>us peace with God, and quiet amongſt men:</hi> There was never ſuch a mocking of God ſince the world ſtood: for men that have profeſſed Chriſt our peace ſo long as you have done, ſhould now tall from that atonement (which you only talked of, had not in power) to offer up to God the bloud of men, the bloud of men already in affliction, the bloud of their enemies, and that upon ſuch principles to ſecure themſelves, to obtain and keep ſelf-advantages; 'tis ſuch a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice as was never yet by the darkeſt heathens invented: if you had covertly ſought revenge upon him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> you had had ſome equals and examples for your fact; but to doe the ſame thing (in feare and revenge to remove an adverſary) and boldly, impudently, to bring it to God as a ſacrifice to appeaſe his diſpleaſure, and expiate ſin, is an unparalel'd wickednes: and a project as foolishly contriv'd, to quiet the people by taking away a <hi>Prince</hi> beloved of his people, indeer'd to them by his <hi>ſufferings;</hi> whoſe government (though ful of weaknes) was far better then thoſe that ſucced <hi>him;</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:116157:26"/>a Prince, ſtrong in the affection of his Subjects, and forain alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and then when he is in a yeelding way to peace, to give ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to his Subjects, yea, when he is upon an agreement, then to ſeeke the removal of him by death, or depoſure againſt the deſires of the bodie of the Kingdome, and of their repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives in Parliament; upon the foul and black deſigns of a few un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing people, that this ſhould be a way to quiet the Kingdome it's as far from policy as the other is from piety.</p>
            <p>But to your Propoſals; firſt, you propound, <hi>That that capitall and grand author of our troubles, the Perſon of the King, may be brought to juſtice for the treaſon, blood, &amp;c.</hi> Two things we wil conſider.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Your Juſtice.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The perſon upon whom 'tis to be adminiſtred.</p>
            <p>Firſt, 'Tis not juſtice that you deſire, it appears ſo to your blinde and deceived hearts; but in the face of God it appears farre otherwiſe: To tel you that juſtice muſt be done by law, and that no law takes hold of the King, will not convince you, though to others it wil manifeſt that; you that pretend to contend for the laws, are the greateſt violaters of them. But the ſearcher of hearts will deale otherwiſe with you, and ſhew you what's within you, and diſcover the falſhood and injuſtice of your ſpirits.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Know this (for you have felt it) that God hath a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy with you: that though you have done many things for him, yet you are not perfect; but there is ſome wicked thing to be purged out of you, which is your glorying in that fleſhly way in which you are: God hath called you out of it, and you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed him, and ſunke down deeper into it, bleſſing add ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning your ſelves in it; being unwilling to ſtrip your ſelves naked of thoſe carnal1 helps and advantages that you were engaged to; or to ſuffer a loſſe of thoſe glorious favours that you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, that you might have better: but loving this <hi>preſent evil world,</hi> and deſpiſing the Spirit of God and refuſing his ſafety a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and to reſt and live under his wings abhorring to ceaſe acting in the fleſh, and to be <hi>perfected by ſufferings:</hi> You have, by this joyned your ſelves to the prince of darkneſſe, departed from God to the God of this world, by which Satan hath betrayed you, ſpoyled all your glory; gotten thoſe good things God gave you, into his poſſeſſion, and imployes them againſt the Lord, and takes the poor people of God captive, to ſerve in the foule and baſe waies of the world; and the Lord now comes for juſtice againſt
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:116157:26"/>
               <hi>this ſpirituall wickedneſſe in places;</hi> you have dealt againſt ſmall petty corruptions and have ſeen them executed; but now the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil hath corrupted all your gifts and graces, and ſpilt the bloud of Chriſt, who was a babe in you, and brought great ſpirituall miſchiefs upon you, death, wrath, trouble, abſence of God, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived you of your freedome with God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> now God cals for juſtice againſt this deſtroyer of ſuch precious beginnings of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and creates trouble in your ſpirit for want of it: but this cunning ſerpent beguiles you and ſets up a ſhadow of an enemy a King without, as an object to your juſtice, to ſave himſelfe and all his villany from the juſtice of God within: Poor beguild wretches, you are not yet acquainted with his wiles: you are turned out of the righteous way, and will never finde peace till you come to ſee all thoſe evils in your ſelves in truth, which are in ſhew and ſhadow in the King; and when the ſword of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which cuts inwardly, is turned againſt thoſe enemies of God you will doe juſtice indeed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, This way of acting in you for juſtice, is great apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, for a company of men that have been led up into ſuch high things of God, to live in God, and doe all things in the Spirit of God; now to fall down into the way of heathens; to lay the weight of their ſpirits upon ſo poor a thing as moral juſtice, and to daunce after the example, or take for their guide and rule the blinde actings of Gentiles that <hi>lived in the world without God;</hi> and onely ſought an outward freedome: and to proſtitute the Spirit of God to ſuch Common and prophane things, is exceeding unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the profeſſion of a Chriſtian, and a going back from <hi>Canaan</hi> to <hi>Aegypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Your Juſtice is but a bare name, or a heathen co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering, borrowed from men to hide your ſhame, your malice, unbeliefe, feare, and ſuch like monſtrous luſts, which you know you are not free from; and though you would not ſee, you ſhall ſee, and the world ſhall ſee too, that you are as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men are, and take up the lees and dregs of the world: cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning waies to remove adverſaries, to take away thoſe that ſtand in your way; and paint them over with the names of juſtice, ſecurity to the publique intereſt, and ſo act them in the face of the Sunne. Take but this inſtance; hundreds of the Kings party, the baſeſt and worſt of them who have borne armes for the King;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:116157:27"/>are yet admitted into your Army, joyned with you in engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; becauſe it is for your advantage end the ſtrengthning your ſelves; to let goe the principal and puniſh inferiour instruments, ſay you, is not juſt: And ſo ſpare inferiours to ſerve us, and puniſh great ones to ſecure our ſelves of them, it is great injuſtice: It is an old deceit of juſtice to lay hold of ſmall offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, and let goe the great ones, that is groſſe and common: but to accept the ſmall ones into, alliance, favour and ſervice becauſe we want their bodies; and to ſeeke the ruine of great ones, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we would have their honours, places and eſtates, is a new wickedneſſe, a path not trodden in before; high flying and gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant cruelty, ſpare rogues, ſlaves to doe ſlaviſh worke, men of no conſcience, worth nor honeſty, and ſtrike at a Prince ſtanding for his intereſt engaged by conſcience and honour: This is your ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</p>
            <p>Now for the King, againſt whom you goe in ful cry; I have this to ſay to check your violent courſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That he had and hath a true lawful right in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and to the Kingdome, as good as any man hath to any thing he poſſeſſes, his crown, revenue and dignity is as righteouſly his birth-right and inheritance as anothers houſe or land; and he that denies this is wilfully blinde.</p>
            <p>As he hath a right to his Crown and Subjects, ſo it is his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples right to have a King, I confeſſe it my birth-right to have relation to a King, to live under a great Monarch; and if I am denyed it, I am denyed my native right, and ſo my pleaſure of honouring and ſerving him, and receiving honour from him, and many and great profits comming by him.</p>
            <p>And he having a right to his Crown, and his People a right to him, it was as juſt for him and his party to ſtand for their right as for any other party to uphold theirs: It is true his inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and Parliaments, and Peoples were all in the darke, and none could diſtinctly divide one from another, or clearly judge which is which; and ſo ordained by God for the fall of them as they ſtood in a worldly way: It is true the King abuſed his intereſt and power, and in the exerciſe of it tranſgreſſed againſt GOD and his People. And it is as true, when the Parliament came to plead their right, they were to ſeeke, and did in contending for it ſinne againſt GOD and the King
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:116157:27"/>ſo that both have a right, both have ſome reaſon to contend for their right, but both have erred in maintaining their rights; And therefore the King is not free from ſinne alone, nor guilty alone, nor his party: The Parliament not free alone, nor guilty alone, but each ſide have ſome good and evill mingled together, you nor they perfectly righteous, all have tranſgreſſed and gone out of the way; and therefore tis pride and partiality in you to ſay he is guilty of all the bloud, rapine, &amp;c. No, all are guilty; We muſt ſay, <hi>There it none righteous, no not one:</hi> You may ſay he was firſt guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or moſt guilty, becauſe he is firſt and greateſt, and ſo hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered firſt &amp; moſt: but to clear your ſelves as pure only, &amp; condemn others as guilty onely, is pride and uncharitableneſſe; and all proceedings upon this ground, are acts of hoſtility, and a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued proſecution of the old difference.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ſay that the King in his preſent ſtate is more righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous then you, he now ſuffers and acts, and is in his preſent way the moſt juſt in the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Firſt, He hath confeſſd his errour, though you wickedly urge it againſt him; and though it be in weakneſſe, yet the Lord is ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of him in it: He hath expreſly own'd his ſinne, and the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament implicitly in yeilding to treat with him, and ſhewing a readineſſe to receive him to favour: Tis in their hearts that they were raſh, violent, and too captious and ready to take advantages againſt the King, being ſpurd on by ſome carnall and ſmiſter ends; and ſo farre as they incline to acknowledge their errours, they are in a way to pardon: Onely you juſtifie your ſelves as innocent, and ſo moſt or 1aſt guilty.</p>
            <p>Secondly, He hath beene in this Treaty in a ſelf-denying way, in a way of parting with his rights, though miſinterpreted, b ing looked upon through enmity and jealouſyes, and you and the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament are upon the gaining and ſecuring to your ſelves: He is coming downe, you and others are getting up: He is falling, you riſing: He is a ſufferer, you inflicters of ſufferings.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, He ownes a God in the world, and appeales to him: that principle that you diſdain ſo much, pag. 47. and elſewhere, is more righteous then yours, which are ſeeking to ſet up a darke forme of Government without God; ſo juſt as not to need God; in which we may reſt, and never goe further to appeale to God. The King hath appeald to God, and it hath coſt him deare; God hath judged him for his ſinnes, as you ſay often in your Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:116157:28"/>and tis a wonder to me that you ſhould fleight that maxim of impunity from man, <hi>and appealing, to God,</hi> when God is come forth ſo viſibly as he is, to puniſh all ill government: Yea, that which you fly to your ſelves in your <hi>ſecond Declaration,</hi> and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God is as righteous to you as to the King, to puniſh you in your kinde as him in his: And as it hath beene his fall, ſo it will be his and your riſing, ſticking faſt to your <hi>appeale to God in diſtreſſe,</hi> he will reſtore him and you.</p>
            <p>A fourth is this, That the King in his offers of peace hath ſhewd a fatherly and large ſpirit, and endeavoured the comprehending of all intereſts; and you inſiſt only upon your own, and others, as relating to yours.</p>
            <p>The fifth and laſt thing I have to ſay for the King, is that which I have already publiſhed, <hi>That he is an Image of the glory of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and choſen by the divine majeſty to bring forth it ſelfe: <hi>A veſſell of honour,</hi> pardoned, loved, and taken into union with God.</p>
            <p>And tis not the leaſt aggravation of your ſinne that you goe on in your waies againſt him, after the divine Grace had ſo publiquely ownd him: And this you doe without any knowledge of the mind of God, or any ability to ſhew the evill &amp; weakneſſe of that diſcovery; but in a rude and brutiſh purſuing of your owne ſenſe and experience: you are ſunke deepe into the earth, or elſe you would not ſay (after ſuch a manifeſt judgement given by God) as you doe, pag. 48. <hi>If they claime by immediate, divine deſignation, let them ſhew it,</hi> pag. 50. in a way of rejecting and denying at leaſt; <hi>Which we are ſure can be no leſſe then ſomething of Divinity:</hi> Indeed you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, nay will not ſee divine things amongſt men, elſe you would not now ſay, <hi>Let them ſhew it.</hi> But of all tis the greateſt wonder that you ſhould be ſuch oppoſers of <hi>Divinity and divine deſignation,</hi> who have profeſſed <hi>God is in all,</hi> there is nothing but God, and cry up the name of God ſo much to be in your owne darke and confuſed wayes, and will not acknoeledge him in any thing that is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable or excellent: And though your Remonſtrance be againſt this glory of God breaking forth in the King, your actions ſhall and doe promote it: and this may be your comfort, that theſe ſufferings will ſo refine and improve him, that he will appeare in that excellent ſpirit of love and goodneſſe, as ſhall freely forgive your violence againſt him, and rejoice in his ſufferings, being the certaine way to a true Throne of Glory. Thus I dare meet with al
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:116157:28"/>your power, and interpoſe betweene the edge of your inflamed wrath and the King; I value not what you can doe or ſay: If you ſay I am turnd Royaliſt, I am of a <hi>Royall Seed,</hi> a <hi>Royall Prieſthood,</hi> and a lover of Royalty in the moſt High God, and no where elſe: If you ſay I doe it upon carnal grounds, you may ſay it, but ſhal not long thinke it, but wil wiſh your ſelves as free from worldly reſpects and ſelfe-ſeeking in acting againſt, as I am in appearing for the <hi>King</hi> ere long.</p>
            <p>The three next things propounded are but the raveling out of the ſame principle; wherein you ſhew what a reach your great feares have, and how wary you are to fortifie your ſelves againſt al from whom there may be any appearance of danger; And ſo the <hi>Kings Children</hi> muſt ſuffer, <hi>and a competent number of his chiefe Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents.</hi> There is here nothing of a new principle, and therefore I omit it.</p>
            <p>Your ſift is, for ſatisfaction of Arrears: This is a main wheel, though it makes little noiſe here; For I believe, if you could get your Arrears, which are very conſiderable ſummes of money, and would helpe you to live conveniently, and could rationally and upon viſible grounds promiſe your ſelves ſafety and a quiet life, you would be content to lay downe many of you and be quiet. This is good ſober dealing, and you thinke it very juſtifiable, <hi>For the Labourer is worthy of his hire;</hi> And you know many of you, I thinke the greateſt part of the body, would have left long agoe, if they had not hoped to recover ſome good part of their Arrears. But is this ſutable to our profeſſion when we undertooke this Warre? Did not we ſcorne a mercenary ſouldier, or ſouldier of fortune? And upon thoſe termes have dealt with God and men; yet now the Kingdome muſt lye under miſery till you have your arrears. I'le but ſay this to you, you are upon as good a way to pay or acquit your Arrears as the <hi>Scots</hi> were.</p>
            <p>Your next thing propounded is concerning the Parliament, that it ſhould have a <hi>Certaine period, and ſo the great truſt repoſed in them may returne to the people, pag.</hi> 65. This Parliament hath beene a pretty hackney for you, you can ride it as long as you will, and which way you wil, and then turne it up: Preſcribe it what it ſhal doe, and how long: Wee ſee now your <hi>tender regard to the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of Parliament:</hi> How pitifully you uſe this <hi>Old Maſſe,</hi> as you cal it, pag. 45. You <hi>guard</hi> it and regard it, mould and turne this maſſe til it be fit for your purpoſe; and when it hath dethron'd
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:116157:29"/>the King and enthrond your government, you will releaſe them and ſend them packing: You are as the Sea, boundleſſe, let looſe from all ties and obligations of ſuperiours, and none can ſtand before you: You trample upon Parliament as well as upon King, impriſon him, and force theſe to doe your worke, and then a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod.</p>
            <p>At laſt you ſhew us the grounds that you would have the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſetled upon, pag. 66. which I ſhal not much meddle with in particular: Onely conſider,</p>
            <p>Firſt, That you profeſſe your ſelves (and tis your property) to be appointed and cald for breaking in pieces the powers of the world, and to be <hi>As the Potſtheards of the earth, that daſh one againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> And in this you are very skilful and able: But what then have you to doe with ſetling? Tis not your trade; you were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver cut out for it, nor bound
'prentiſe to it; and ſo it ſeemes by the grounds you lay <hi>of common right;</hi> which are onely framd with reſpect to your owne private intereſt, and have little <hi>of right freedom or common</hi> in them, onely much <hi>of ſafety</hi> for your ſelves, as you thinke: Why doe you diſſemble with men, holding forth a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to ſettle the Kingdome, when you know al things are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetling, and for that you act.</p>
            <p>Or if this be a ground laid for future ſettlement and ſafety, its a wofull <hi>Babel,</hi> an Idol, a lye, a vanity, a thing that cannot ſave: <hi>Will this reach to heaven,</hi> or ſave you from the floud of wrath that is broken out upon you? Tis an unprofitable, empty, deſolate thing, <hi>A veſſell in which is no pleaſure,</hi> neither inward nor outward; Like the image of <hi>Dagon,</hi> fallen, and without his head; You would thinke it Apoſtacy for men to goe backe to 10 or 20 years ſince, but to plead for an age before the conqueſt, and run backe to to the moſt barbarous times; not only from God, to the glory of great ſtates, but to <hi>Egypts Garlicke and Onions,</hi> to the dul, ſenſeleſſe people, and ſet them up, as Idols, to ſave you, and fall downe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this wood and ſtone, as things of <hi>vaſt concernment:</hi> What a condition are you ſhrunk into? <hi>Enſnard in holes of earth.</hi> Here lies the glory of your Saintſhip, of your Kingdome of God, or this is the end of al your carnal and fleſhly religion: This is the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you ſettle in, the grounds of your peace; <hi>The Lord marches thorow the land in indignation, and wounds the head out of the houſe of the wicked, by diſcovering the foundations to the weak; Thou didſt ſtrike thorow, with his ſtaves, the head of the villages; Thou haſt wounded the head, the</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:116157:29"/>glory of the Kingdome, and now thou ſtrikeſt thorow the <hi>head of villages, not onely deſtroy royall,</hi> but <hi>popular power,</hi> and doſt rip up the foundations, and ſhew the folly, rottenneſſe and ungodlineſſe of the loweſt ſtones as wel as of the higheſt; None ſhall eſcape thy Righteo is iudgements.</p>
            <p>Your laſt thing propounded <hi>is a contract or agreement;</hi> a contract or bargaine, not a marriage, for there is no husband; <hi>An agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with death,</hi> no life, no God; no, wee have enough of them; Alas, they are poore things, they will not hold a quarter of a year; a cobling device: Let us have a Saviour that can defend himſelfe, and needs not to be tied together, and <hi>naild faſt</hi> by an agreement or contract: this is a poore God; an old Canonical trick, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions; Conformity for State as wel as for Church; <hi>That none be capable of any benefit by it but ſuch as ſubſcribe; None beare any office or place of publique truſt; nor King except be ſubſcribe;</hi> This is <hi>publique li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and common right:</hi> There was never groſſer tyranny ever ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peard in the world: Tis I am very ſure, the laſt and worſt piece of folly (in this kinde) that ever was brought forth; And after the caſting off al powers, breaking al Covenants, this comes in as a crowne of the worke, <hi>a great chaine of darkneſſe,</hi> to binde us to the earth for ever; a great bog, in which we may lye faſt: Where is that liberty of the ſpirit, that glory of God that ſhould make men confeſſe God <hi>is in you of a truth? This is your binding Kings in chaines of Iron:</hi> Did ever men fall from praying for, profeſſing of, preaching of, aiming at the <hi>laſt and great glory of God?</hi> as you do to ſuch a beggarly rudiment, as agreement with the people, ſubſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon penalty. Your condition is well expreſſed, <hi>Iſay.</hi> 65. 4, 5. Which ſay, <hi>Stand by thy ſelfe, come not neare me, for I am holier then thou.</hi> You ſay to the King, Biſhops and Presbyters, ſtand by, thruſt them away, and their oaths, conformities, covenants; ſtand by al you Eccleſiaſtical ſubſcriptions, we wil have a civill one: You requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſome, we wil have al ſubſcribe: We are the moſt Righteous that have come yet, none before us did ſuch things as we; <hi>And yet,</hi> ſaith the Text, <hi>Which lye amongſt the graves:</hi> You lye downe in the rotten Sepulchres of the Biſhops; their waies are dead and putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and you goe downe into them, and defile your ſelves with them, <hi>And lodge in the monuments:</hi> You have ſtriven long for refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and for the Kingdome of God, but at laſt wildred and nighted, you take up your reſt and lodging amongſt the dried bones of your dead anceſtors, would ſave your ſelves by oaths, ſubſcriptions, &amp;c. which are the great ſignes of the uncertainty
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:116157:30"/>and mortality of ſtates; when they finde they begin to dye, they ſet up their memories on theſe monuments of Covenants and Subſcriptions: And <hi>eate ſwines fleſh;</hi> that's another evil; You live upon that beaſt, a ſwine that loves digging and rooting in the earth: You are not content with what the earth, by the favour of heaven, ſends forth, but are digging into, and turning up the bowels of the Kingdome to ſatisfie your ſwiniſh appetites: Or love to wallow in mire, and to lye upon the dunghil of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes confuſions, and take pleaſure in it: <hi>And broth of abhominable things;</hi> you abhominate tyranny, compulſion, enforcing in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to impoſe and advance their owne intereſt; but refuſing to doe the thing it ſelfe, you eate <hi>the broth,</hi> doe the ſame thing in a looſer, weaker, baſer and more ſervile way.</p>
            <p>You are the lees and dregs of the world, the taile of it; you thinke you are the beſt, but are the worſt; for the world growes worſe and worſe, and the deeper you goe into it, the further you are from God, and the neerer to hel, to confuſion; for the world hath its foundations in the deeps: Tis a fond conceit ariſing from the groſſeſt ignorance and ſelf-love, to thinke that you are better then others, al your waies being more abſurd, violent, irratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, then the worſt of thoſe that have gone before you: You may reade your deſcription excellently penned long agoe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, <hi>&amp;c. Now the ſpirit ſpeaketh expreſly; He ſpeakes</hi> to whom all times are <hi>now,</hi> who ſees all things preſent: <hi>He ſpeakes</hi> truth, things are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he <hi>ſpeakes</hi> them: Therefore doth your glory fade away, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſpirit of the Lord hath blowd upon it, and he ſpeaks expreſly;</hi> There's nothing the Lord brings forth more exactly, fully and clearly, then the apoſtacy of carnal profeſſours; a worke wherein be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights to be compleat, and to doe it to the life; to fil religious fleſh, kicking againſt him, with abſurd folly and groſſe wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: <hi>In the latter times,</hi> which are theſe daies, when time growes low, tis the worſt: That time wherein we are looking for the greateſt good, then appeares the greateſt evill.</p>
            <p>And that in Apoſtates <hi>Some ſhall depart from the faith;</hi> the ſpirit ſaies now expreſly you are theſe ſome; you have departed from the faith.</p>
            <p>Firſt, From the doctrine of faith, expreſſed in the laſt verſe of the former Chapter, and in the 6. v. of this Chapter, <hi>In the words of faith and good doctrine:</hi> The moſt forward of you in religion doe depart from the chiefe and maine doctrines of Chriſt; and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe nor can hold forth thoſe myſteries, <hi>God manifeſt in the fleſh,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:116157:30"/>&amp;c.</hi> And from al rule of faith you doe depart by profeſſion and practiſe: to ſpeak to you concerning thoſe commands of ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Kings, Superiours, &amp;c. is literal, legal, you have a ſpirit above thoſe commands, and thoſe concerning the worſhip of God, you are above Ordinances, &amp;c. and ſo falling into a ſtate of liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and looſeneſſe from al lawes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, You have departed from what you have believed, which was the <hi>Kingdome of Chriſt,</hi> purity of religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> into le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veling, irreligious, worldly principles, <hi>giving heed to ſeducing ſpirits:</hi> you talke of the Spirit, but are led by an <hi>unclean ſpirit, a falſe ſpirit,</hi> or <hi>an erring and ſeducing ſpirit;</hi> the devil and your owne luſts have carried you away from the way of Chriſt, which is by the Croſſe, to aſcend to glory, by ſuffering to reigning; but that way you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline and fall upon worldly conteſts for worldly things: I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at your groſſe deceit, <hi>deceiving and being deceived</hi> (did I not know your hearts <hi>are made groſſe and fat, that you are given up to ſtrong deluſions, to believe a lye</hi>) that you ſhould pretend to be led by God in your waies, and that he goes before you, and yet are in ſuch darkneſſe (as your ſelves profeſſe) you ſee not a foot before you; but attend every day for new leadings, new diſcoveries of the minde of God: into what a miſerable labyrinth hath the devil led you! to goe blindly and confidently after your owne imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations which are confuſed, darke, and uncertain, and cauſe you to attend to thoſe motions and actings, and tell you 'tis the Spirit of the Lord. No no, The Spirit of God is light, clearneſſe, ſtability; 'tis that <hi>Anointing whereby we know all things, from firſt to laſt,</hi> he <hi>leads us in plain paths;</hi> in waies of order, peace, goodneſſe: I abhorre that that blind mole, that bat, that dusky night-owle, that halting, blind thing which you follow, ſhould be cald by the name of God or the ſpirit of God; <hi>Doctrines of Devils,</hi> of wrath, malice, accuſations, diſorders, confuſions, deſtructions, or as <hi>Mead</hi> interprets <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of earthly, humane, petty Gods or Saints; ſuch are your Gods humane, earthly, weake Gods, that have no glory, majeſty nor excellency in them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſ.</hi> 2. <hi>Speaking lyes in hypocriſie;</hi> Your juſtice, publique intereſt, common right are al lyes; and ſo are <hi>all men,</hi> and things of <hi>men</hi> but a <hi>lye;</hi> and <hi>you ſpeake them in hypocriſie,</hi> cunningly, to deceive and ſeeke your ſelves, and your owne intereſt, <hi>Having their conſcience ſcard with a hot iron:</hi> God hath ſet ſome brands and marks of favour upon you, given you ſome victories and ſucceſſe, to inſnare your proud hearts, to ſat up the fleſh for its deſtruction: This, and your
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:116157:31"/>fiery, zeale for <hi>justice,</hi> for <hi>common good,</hi> which is a baſe mettal, at beſt <hi>iron</hi> (made to breake things in pieces) but theſe, as <hi>a hot iron,</hi> doe ſo hiſſe in your mindes, and ſmoke in your eyes, that you cannot heare the voice of God, nor ſee his waies; you are ſo obdurate up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe things, <hi>Gods glorious preſence with you, the wonders he hath done by you:</hi> (things common to <hi>Alexander, Caeſar;</hi> and many Heathens more in a greater way then ever you had them) that you think it impiety, malignancy, &amp;c. once to queſtion your way.</p>
            <p>All the reſt concernes you, <hi>Forbidding to marry,</hi> you forbid hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth to marry; forbid King and people to marry; and the ſame ſpirit goes ſo farre in ſome, as to deny marriage, and to maintaine a community amongſt men and women, becauſe <hi>In the reſurrection there is neither marrying nor giving in marriage. To abſtaine from meats;</hi> Many things you would have men abſtain from, Kings, Lords, Tithes, and many other <hi>good creatures of God,</hi> that your ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack cannot digeſt, and you forbid others the uſe of them, becauſe you are not <hi>ſanctified,</hi> neither doe you ſee them <hi>ſanctified</hi> by the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall <hi>word and prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You are drawing towards an end, and here I ſhall joine iſſue with you, pag. 69. <hi>That ſince the heart of man is deceitfull and corrupt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things, and moſt apt to anſwerable counſels and actings where it can hope to walk in the dark, undiſcernd and undiſtinguiſht:</hi> therefore you deſire <hi>liberty of entring diſſents:</hi> Upon this ground doe I deſire liberty to enter my diſſent from you, and upon what followes in your words, <hi>In theſe tranſactions of ſuch high moment to the publique and all honeſt intereſts, and in times ſo apt to deceit, defection and apoſtacy.</hi> With you, pag. 70. I profeſſe, <hi>That as the exigence of the caſe, and nature of the buſineſſe requires (being of ſuch vaſt importance to all publique, religious and honeſt intereſt, not in this Kingdom only, but in neighbour nations) I have dealt with al plainnes and clearnes, as God hath enabled me. And now to conclude, we hope that in an age of ſo much light; meer wil and reſolution wil not be held forth and purſued againſt it: But that what reaſon and righteouſnes there is in the things we have ſaid, wil be conſidered and followed.</hi> Tis my requeſt to you in your own words, &amp; that you would not in prejudice or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain lay theſe things aſide; but that you would, ſetting aſide your preſent actings of leſſe importance far, yea, of certain danger &amp; ruin to your ſelvs and others, you would conſider what I have here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in love to you, <hi>&amp; for your good &amp; ſafety, &amp; the peace of the Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that being often reproved hardneth his necke, ſhall ſuddenly be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and that without remedy.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
